What's really interesting about about
this book, Max, is um you know,
obviously I' I've read loads and loads
of books in in the space and there's,
you know, people like Hinton and Hawkins
and Damasio and Friston and uh I mean,
God, you know, even like Sutton and
what's interesting is it's a bit like
the blind men and the elephant. So,
they've all got a completely different
story to tell. And I think the magic
that you have pulled off with this book
is somehow you've woven it together into
a coherent story. like what what do you
think about that?
>> Well, first uh I'm very appreciative of
of the kind words. Yeah, I think I came
from a very unique perspective just
because I was a complete outsider. Um
and I think uh you know and I didn't
come to it with the objective of writing
an academic book at all. I came to it
from the objective I was just learning
on my own. Um, and I just started
building this corpus of notes, um, cuz I
was so independently curious. And I kind
of stumbled on this idea really for
myself of how do I make sense of all of
these disparate opinions um, and really
this complete lack of information about
how the brain actually works. And I had
my own set of I think biases coming from
sort of the technology entrepreneurial
world where uh, we tend to think about
things as ordered modifications. uh when
you think about product strategies or
how to roll things out, we like to think
about things as what's step one then
what's step two, what's step three. Um
so I think I did have sort of a
cognitive bias to when presented with an
incredible amount of complexity to try
and make sense of it in a similar type
of way. Um um but yeah, I think as an
outsider I felt very free to sort of
explore and cross the boundaries between
fields. I mean I I look at the book as a
merging of three fields. One is
comparative psychology. So trying to
understand what are the different
intellectual capacities of uh different
species. Um evolutionary neuroscience.
So what do we know about the past brains
of humans and the ordered set of
modifications of how brains came to be?
And then AI um which is um how do we
ground sort of the high flutin
conceptual discussions about how the
brain works in what what works in
practice I think is a really important
grounding principle because it helps
really hold us accountable towards the
principles that we think work if we
can't implement them in AI systems it
makes it should make us question if we
actually have the ideas right. Um so so
yeah I think being an outsider in some
ways you know comes with disadvantages
uh um but there are some advantages also
which is you're kind of free to borrow
from a variety of different fields and
think freshly about things.
>> Yes. I mean if you can point to any
particular um ideas that you found
really really difficult to reconcile
what what would those be?
>> One thing that's really challenging is
um if we were to actually lay out uh
what's the data richness of comparative
psychology studies across species. If
you put that on a whiteboard and looked
at it, you would realize we have so
little data um on what intellectual
capacities different animals in fact
have. Um for example, uh the lamprey
fish, which is sort of the canonical uh
animal that's used as a model organism
for the first vertebrates. Um because
it's the of of all vertebrates alive
today, it's one of our most distant
vertebrae cousins. To my knowledge,
there are absolutely no studies
examining the map-based navigation of
the lamp prey fish. So, so we have no
idea if it's in fact capable of
recognizing things in 3D space. Now,
when we look at other vertebrates like
tio fish, it seems like they're
eminently capable of doing that. We look
at lizards, they're eminently capable of
doing that. So, we we sort of infer um
it seems likely that the first ver
vertebrates were able to do this. We
know the brain structures from which it
emerges and and reptiles um and tilios
fish are present in the lamprey. So, we
we sort of back into an inference that
okay, probably the lamprey fish can do
that. Um but this is all sort of uh in
some sense guessing and trying to put
the pieces together from very little
information. So I think that's one
challenging uh aspect to reconcile. Um
the other one uh that's really hard uh
is
in in neuroscience there's a lot of
really interesting ideas um about how
the brain might work that have not
really been tested in the wild um from
the an AI perspective and then there's a
lot of uh AI systems that work really
well that have diverged substantially
from at least the evidence what the
evidence suggests is how brains work. So
how do you bridge the gap between these
two things? I think is a really
fascinating
uh space to operate in which is like
what can we learn about the brain if
anything from the success of
transformers as an example. Um what can
we learn if anything from the success of
generative models in general? Um what
can we learn from the success of and
failures of modern reinforcement
learning? I mean in some ways
reinforceable learning has been a
success in other ways it's really uh
fallen short of what a lot of people
hoped it would be. Um so I think the the
gap between neuroscience and AI is still
a challenging one. uh to bridge in a lot
of ways. Um for example, Carl Fson has
all these incredible ideas in active
inference. Um in a hundred years, will
we look back on this and be like Carl
Fen was on to something. Um if you look
at the AI systems today, there's very
little, you know, usage of active
inference principles working in
practice. Um so that could mean that the
ideas don't have legs or it could mean
that there's a breakthrough behind the
corner where we're actually missing some
of the key principles that he's
devising. And these are, you know,
questions we don't have the answers to.
I think there might possibly be some
breakthroughs around the corner. I don't
know if you know, but I'm I'm Carl
Friston's personal publicist. Um I I do
all of his stuff. I I I probably
interviewed him more than anyone else,
but I love my friend. He's an amazing
guy. Yeah, he's an amazing man.
>> Honestly, he he is the man. He is the
man. And um
>> so kind.
>> I know. For me as well, he has so much
time to explain things. But yeah, um you
could cynically argue that, you know,
the the the effective active inference
agent is just a reinforcement learning
agent of a particular variety. I think
it's equivalent to a um like an inverse
reinforcement learning maximum entropy
agent or something. But there's so much
more than that. There's so much richness
and explanatory power of of of kind of
modeling this thing as as a generative
model that can generate um policies and
plans of actions and and so on. And also
we want to have agents that you know we
understand what they're doing and and
like with steerability and being able to
do the simulations that you talk to so
eloquently in in your in your paper but
just I love for instance we'll do we'll
do him properly later but um to come
back to what you were saying though so
you were saying oh you know there might
be a parallel between transformers and
AI models in in your book actually on
this page you you sort of like g you you
kind of analogize um modelbased
reinforcement learning and the neoortex
And of course I interviewed Hawkins back
in the day and the main criticism of his
book is that uh you know the triune
brain type argument. So he's kind of
giving giving the explanation that uh
the brain developed a bit like
geological strata with one layer and
then another layer rather than kind of
co-evolving together. And it's so hard
not to think like that because you give
so many beautiful examples in your book,
not only just morphologically, but but
in terms of capability, how the
neoortex, I mean, you said like with
stroke victims, for example, it's not
like the brain recovers those dead
cells. It learns to kind of repurpose
those functions in other parts of the
brain. So, it seems like Mount Castle
was correct in the neoortex is this just
magic general purpose learning system. I
mean, what do you think?
So I think um well there's two different
uh there's two different ways to look at
uh the neoortex enabling things like
mental simulation and model free or
model based reinforcement learning. One
is that that function and algorithm is
being implemented in the neoortex. But
another which is a slightly less strong
claim which is the one I would make is
the addition of the neoortex enables the
overall system to engage in this
process. So it is not saying that uh the
entire process is implemented in the
neoortex. I think it seems very clear
that the phalamus and basil ganglia are
essential aspects of enabling the
pausing the mental simulation the
modeling of one's own intentions the
evaluation of the results etc. But it is
possibly to say which is what I'm argue
in the book is in the absence of the
neoortex that process does not happen.
Um, and so I think where my ideas would
synergize with what Hawkins is saying is
the neoortex builds a very rich model of
the world and a model of sufficient
richness that you can explore it in the
absence of s sensory input. Um, and
that's a really essential aspect of
model-based reinforcement learning
because if I have a a model of the world
that has sufficient richness that I can
mentally simulate actions um that I'm
not actually taking and it at least
somewhat accurately predicts the real
consequences of those actions. And that
model is really useful um uh because I
can now imagine outcomes before having
them. I can flexibly adjust to new
situations. Um and of course there's so
many really deep interesting questions
that are yet to be answered about that.
For example, um just because you can
render a simulation of the world doesn't
answer the question, okay, what do you
simulate? I mean, this is one of the one
of the hardest problems of model based
reinforcement learning is fine, you can
have a model of the world, but how do
you prune the search space of which
aspects of that model you explore before
evaluating outcomes? Um, and so that's
another really hard challenge that I
think there's a lot of good evidence is
actually a partnership between the
neoortex and the and the basil ganglia,
which is a much older structure. Um, so
yeah, I'm not really of the, you know, I
think the triune brain has been, you
know, amongst evolutionary
neuroscientists largely discredited. Um,
and I think in part somewhat unfairly if
you actually read McClean's writings, he
was he actually is very open about the
fact that, you know, this is an
approximation. It's not exactly
accurate. Like he he couches his claims
much more than the popular culture than
just converted into a dogma. Um but I
think the the popular interpretation of
the triune brain is not accurate which
is it is clearly not the case uh that
the brain evolves in three key layers.
It's not the case that a reptile brain
doesn't have anything limbic like uh if
you the a reptile brain absolutely has a
cortex that does a lot of what our
limbic structures do etc etc. Um so yeah
that those would be my thoughts on that.
>> Yeah it it's fascinating because we as
humans need to have models to explain
and understand the thing itself just
like active inference for example. I
mean, I I'll get to planning and agency
and goals in a little while, but a lot
of these things are instrumental
fictions. I'm not saying [clears throat]
that our brains don't plan, but you
know, like the way that the abstract
mathematical way that we understand
planning, it's probably not how the
brain works. It's it's much more
complicated than that. But why don't we
just rewind to the beginning? So, you
know, we're going to be talking about
this chapter on on, you know, simulation
if you like. And you kind of lead by
saying that what the neoortex does is it
does learning by imagining. And uh
Hawkins spoke about this as well. He
said we've got the matrix inside our
brains, right? We're always just doing
all of these simulations of of future
things. And uh we're using that to kind
of help us understand the world. And you
you give this really interesting example
of um some of the features of the brain
that kind of lead you to believe that we
are basically living in a simulation.
And it's almost like rather than
perceiving things, we're testing if our
simulation is correct, but that means
that we can only simulate one thing at a
time. So we can't we can't see two
things. We can only see one thing. So
can can you talk through that?
>> Sure. So um one of the um first sort of
introspections and explorations into how
perception works in the human mind
happened in the late 19th century with
all of these explorations of visual
illusions that you see in pretty much
every neuroscience textbook or book that
you open. Um so listeners will be
familiar with you've probably seen
examples of triangles where you actually
perceive a triangle in a picture when
there is in fact no triangle. Um or uh
yes that isn't that yeah you can find
that picture. [laughter] Uh
>> yeah sorry I hope I'm not distracting
you.
>> No no no. So that's um so that's a you
know a standard uh finding that was
observed in the 19th century which is
this idea that clearly the brain
observes the presence of things even
though they're not actually there. So we
perceive a triangle there, we perceive a
sphere. We perceive sort of a bar. we
perceive the word editor when in fact if
you actually examine that the word E is
not there. Um there's evidence that
suggests E is there by virtue of showing
the shadows but we did not actually
write the letter E there but the brain
regularly observes that. Um so that
finding led uh this this uh scientist
Herman von Helmholtz to sort of come up
with this concept that what the brain
what you actually consciously perceive
is not your sensory stimuli. You are not
receiving sensory input and experiencing
the sensory input. What's happening is
your brain is making an inference as to
what is true in the world, what's
actually there and then the evidence is
just uh the sensory input is giving
evidence to your brain as to what's
there. And so you start from this prior
um and then that prior maintains itself
until you get sufficient evidence to the
contrary and then you change your mind.
And so it's not hard to imagine why this
would be extremely useful in uh any sort
of environment um that an animal might
evolve in. You know, suppose you have uh
a mouse running across a tree branch at
night. Um first I see the tree branch
and the moonlight. So I build a mental
model of the tree branch. As I move
forward, I lose moonlight. I no longer
see the tree branch. As long as as I'm
stepping forward, the evidence is
consistent with my prior of the tree
branch. it makes way more sense for me
to maintain the mental model of that
tree branch as opposed to all of a
sudden the tree branch disappears
because I no longer see the sensory
stimuli of it. So because sensory
stimuli is very noisy, it makes a lot of
sense that we in integrate it over time,
build a prior and then until something
uh gives us evidence to the contrary, we
maintain our prior about the world. So
so that was sort of the first idea that
there's some form of inference. there's
some ch there's some difference between
sensory input and some model of the
world that we infer and then thus
perceive. What's interesting that is not
as discussed but is also present in the
discussions amongst scientists in the
late 20th century about this late 19th
century about this is this idea that you
can't actually render a simulation of
two things at once. Um so there's lots
of really interesting uh sort of visual
illusions around this where you can see
something. The famous one is it's either
a duck or a rabbit. Yep. Exactly. And um
it's interesting. Yeah. And then so you
can see that staircase is either moving
up to the left or you're under the
staircase looking upwards um and it's
actually a ceiling that's jagged. Um and
why can't the brain perceive both of
those things at the same time? Well, it
would make sense if you have a model
that there are such things as ducks,
there are such things as rabbits, there
are such things as 3D shapes that
operate under certain assumptions. And
if that's true, then you cannot see a
duck and a rabbit at the same time
because there's no such thing. It cannot
be the case that the staircase is
looking from above and below at the same
time. So what your brain is not doing is
just perceiving the sensory stimuli.
It's trying to infer what is a real 3D
thing in the world that I am aware about
that this sensory stimuli is suggesting
is true and that is the thing that I'm
going to render in your mind. Um, and
uh, I think one way this parallels
nicely to some of Hawkins's ideas
actually is if you hold the thousand
brains theory to be true, which is the
the neoortex has sort of all of these
redundant overlapping models of objects,
then it would make a lot of sense that
we want to synergize these models to
render one thing at a time. You don't
want to have 15 different things
rendered because then it's really hard
to evaluate them and vote between these
different columns. Um, so it makes sense
that the brain does is say, "Let me
integrate all the input across sensory
stimuli and render one sort of symphony
of of models in my mind so I can see one
thing at a time." So that's this idea of
perception by inference. Um, at the time
no one really connected that to the idea
of planning. So this was just this idea
that what we perceive is different from
the sensory stimuli we we uh get. Um but
later on sort of uh as a the world of AI
started thinking about things from the
perspective of perception by inference
um what we end up realizing is this idea
of perception by inference if you're
going to train a model to do that it
comes with this notion of generation um
so uh because the way it self-supervises
is it takes the prior and it tries to
make predictions and it compares the
predictions in the world to the sensory
stimuli and as long as those predictions
are below a threshold I maintain my
prior. Um, so a famous version of this
is the Helm Holtz machine which Hinton
devised. I think that was in the 80s.
Um, it could be later I forget. Yep. And
so this is this basic idea that you can
build a model he called, you know, a lot
of people use the term latent
representation. Some people don't like
that term for a variety of philosophical
reasons. Um, but it builds a
representation of things by virtue of
building a model. Um, in other words,
perception by inference. And the way you
build that model is you're constantly
comparing generating predictions from
that model to what actually occurs. And
this also has synergies to a lot of
Hawkins's ideas where uh we think about
intelligence as prediction. Um and so um
what that means is if you if you build a
model of perception by inference by
virtue of generation then it's
relatively easy to say okay well what
happens if I just turn off sensory
stimuli and I start exploring the latent
representation. Well now we're exploring
a simulated world. Um, I'm able to cut
off sensory stimuli, close my eyes, and
imagine a chair, rotate the chair,
change the color of the chair. And
because this model is a relatively good,
uh, has relatively rich features about
how the world actually works, um, I can
model things without ever having
experienced them, um, without ever
having done them and relatively
reasonably predict what what, um, is
real is would actually happen if I were
to do those things. So what I think is
interesting and perhaps somewhat of a
novel uh um [clears throat]
uh proposal in the book is I think a lot
of people think about the neoortex as
having adaptive value because of how
good it is at recognizing things in the
world. Right? So a lot you know if you
read a standard uh textbook a lot of
what people will talk about the neoortex
is how good it is at perceiving things
object recognition. Um some of the best
studied parts of the brain are this
visual neoortex. So we understand
reasonably well how we're building
models of visual objects etc. But from
an evolutionary perspective this is a
little bit hard uh to to find convincing
because if you actually examine the
object recognition of vertebrates it's
incredibly accurate. I mean a fish can
recognize human faces. Um a fish can
oneot recognize an object when rotated
in 3D space. So, it's hard to find a
dividing line between object recognition
in animals with a neoortex and object
recognition in objects without a
neoortex and with uh with brain
structures that seem more similar to
early vertebrates.
>> Um, did you have a question? Yeah.
>> Well, well, yeah, I just wanted to touch
on a couple things there. So um Hawkins
said that the reason I mean he said
first of all that we overcome the
binding problem by having this kind of
profusion of individual sensory motor
models rather than having this
[clears throat] kind of you know feed
forward enrichment of representations
>> and that was really interesting but he
also said the reason why having let's
say we've got 150,000 mini cortical
columns that are just wired to different
sensory motor signals and he said it's
the it's the kind of diversity and
sparsity that gave the robustness of
recognition And then you can kind of
think okay well well what do the
representations look like? So if our
brain builds some kind of a a model of
the world some kind of topological model
it it must be a representation not
necessarily it's not like a a hunulous
or it's not like a stapler inside the
brain if I'm modeling a stapler it's
actually some weird structure of the
stapler but as seen by every way I can
touch feel here and you know lick a
stapler or whatever. So it's difficult
for us to imagine what that is. But the
reason I'm the reason I'm going down
this road though because that's a bit
weird, isn't it? So we have this very
weird representation of things and then
I come to Hinton's um Helm Holtzian
generative model and you can get it to
generate let's say a number eight if
it's trained to do numbers right and
Hinton would argue and I would disagree
with him that that the model understands
what an eight is. Now, this is weird,
isn't it? Because we understand what a
mouse is, but intuitively we feel that a
neural network doesn't understand what
an eight is. And I would argue that
we're getting into semantics here. So, I
think the reason we understand things is
because there's a relational component
to understanding. So, semantics is is
about the ontology. you know our rep the
way we feel about things where the thing
came from what was the intention guiding
the creation of the thing what was the
provenence of the thing it's almost like
the interconnectedness of the thing
tells you more about the meaning of the
thing than the actual thing itself in a
weird way what what do you think
>> well I do think I think uh this is where
uh the word understanding I think can
mean different things to different
people can understand the word
understanding in different ways Um I
think there is absolutely
uh something to the idea that uh just
because you can recognize something. So
that would be a feed forward network
that can observe a stapler. Um uh alone
is insufficient to what most people
would mean when they use the word
understanding. Um and just to talk about
interrelatedness, if I have a feed
forward network that you know let's say
it's just a binary classifier, is this
thing a stapler or not? Um, now I can't
ask lots of things of that feed forward
network that I would expect of a uh an
agent or a model that understands what a
stapler is. I couldn't ask it, for
example, what would happen if I uh
burned the stapler? What would happen if
I opened it? What would you see inside
of it? I can't ask um what does a
stapler do? Um I can't say show show a
human holding a stapler and a set of
objects in front of them and what do you
think the person's going to do next with
this stapler? And so and so clearly
understanding most of our intuitive
understanding of the word understanding
um contains some richness that's not
included in just classifying or
recognizing the presence of objects. So
I think that's absolutely the case. Um
my intuitions sort of fall in the
direction of uh what we mean typically
when we use the word understanding it
comes to having something that can be
mentally explored. Um, and so I think
that could that requires what you're
describing, which is the
interrelatedness of things because when
I see someone holding a stapler and you
ask me the question, what are the things
they would likely do? Well, I start
imagining what they might do with that
stapler and then I can evaluate which
ones seem plausible to me. Um, and so in
the imagination and evaluation of which
things seem plausible, there's an
interconnectedness between the thing and
the the world around it. Um but yes I if
I absolutely agree with you that just
recognizing objects clearly lacks
something that we mean when we say
understanding.
>> Yeah. Do do you take into consideration
the memephere? So you know we've got
this kind of um we've got ideas that are
quite collective as well. I guess I was
going to explore this with you later but
um maybe maybe let me frame it like
this. I I have this um intuition that a
lot of our intelligence is outside of
the brain. So, it's almost like if if I
was in the wilderness and, you know,
disconnected from society, um, I would
be much, you know, a lesser human being.
In a weird way, I might have more
agency, but, you know, I I wouldn't have
access to all of these rich cultural
tools and knowledge and patterns and and
so on. So, it it's almost like that's
where a lot of our intelligence comes
from rather than and and and also
meaning as well rather than than just
being able to plan in the brain and so
on. And there must be some kind of
interplay. So culture must shape the
development of our brain and and vice
versa. But culture seems to be more
dynamic. But how how do you wrestle with
that?
>> Well, I mean there it's that's
undeniably true. I mean uh the the first
example that comes to mind is just
writing. I mean what would humans be if
you removed the technology of writing? I
mean we would we would all realize we're
not that smart. Um I mean writing is a
technology that externalizes a feature
of the brain. Um uh which is memory
which brains are not that great at. Um
we do a good job of like condensing
aspects of a memory. So we uh for
episodic like things and procedural
memory we're relatively good at. Um but
for semantic memories we're terrible. Um
and so externalizing that with writing
is one of the key technologies that
enables us to be way smarter than we are
in fact uh because we now have this
external device that enables us to store
largely infinite numbers of memories and
translate them across generations. So
that alone I think proves your point
which is uh what humans are capable of
is clearly some relationship between
brains and external things that can be
writing tools uh that can be other
brains um you know sharing ideas and
getting challenged. Um so yeah you're
absolutely I agree with you in
>> intelligence is like the it's the
dynamics isn't it? It's it's all of the
low-level, you know, dynamics of things
interacting with each other. And we can
take a snapshot of language and and we
might say, "Oh, well, yeah, you know,
language isn't isn't the intelligence,
but but language itself is a form of
intelligence." I'm not just talking
about the words and language models and
so on. We're talking about the actual
language in in our culture. And I guess
I I think of that as as almost a
distinct form of intelligence.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I mean I I think um it we
all it almost gets into a philosophical
territory as where do you draw the
bounding boxes over the things that are
imbued with intelligence and the things
that are supportive mechanisms that that
allow those things to have intelligence.
So through one lens you could you could
think about brains as the physical
entity in which intelligence is
instantiated and then language is a
supportive tool. You could take a very
perhaps odd view which is language is
the thing that's evolving and it's just
instantiated in these brains that sort
of produce the language, consume the
language, but it's language that's
that's evolving. The same way that you
know we don't think about intelligence
on the level of an individual neuron. Um
we don't imbue a neuron with
intelligence but we think on the scale
of the 86 billion neurons something has
emergently uh appeared that we do deem
intelligent. Um, you know, there's some
great sci-fi books, uh, where, you know,
intelligence gets instantiated in
colonies of ants where each individual
ants isn't not intelligent, but somehow
the colony itself is capable of doing
incredible abstractions and whatever.
So, so yes, I think there's there's very
interesting ways to and it's not obvious
how one divides the lines between what
are the physical entities in which these
are instantiated. That said, I have a
particular interest in brains because I
think if we're looking for
for uh what is the physical
manifestation that we can learn from and
thus try to uh one to understand
ourselves just I think all species have
an interest in understanding ourselves.
Um but then also uh if we want to try
and borrow some ideas from how
biological intelligence works into AI, I
think the of all the physical things to
examine, the brain to me seems clearly
the one that is probably the most rich
with insight. Um but I no I agree. I I
think your point is well taken.
>> Interesting. Okay. Um I want to close
the loop on what what you said about the
brain being an imagination filling in
machine. So you said that it does
filling in. It's one at a time. it can't
unsee visual illusions and evidence is
seen in the wiring of the neoortex
itself you say. So it's um um shown to
have many properties consistent with a
generative model. The evidence is seen
in the surprising symmetry the ironclad
inseparability between perception and
imagination that is found in generative
models in the neoortex. And you give
examples like um um illusions and how
humans succumb to hallucinations why we
dream and sleep and even the inner
workings of imagination itself. So it
really seems plausible when when you
kind of think of it in that way.
>> Yeah. I think I think there's there's a
reason why um so much of the
neuroscience community I mean what I'm
saying there is not really uh novel um
so much the neuroscience community has
sort of rallied around this idea of
predictive coding which is very related
to active inference
um and generative models um because
there's just so much evidence that
what's going on in the neoortex uh the
imagination of things uh episodic
memories I mean it's there's been some
good evidence that epis sodic memory and
in other words thinking about past and
imagining the future are in fact the
same underlying process happening in the
neoortex which is again consistent with
this idea that there's a generative
model um if we look at the connectivity
patterns I didn't talk about this too
deeply in the book is a little technical
but um what you would expect from a
generative model is backwards
connections would be much richer than
forward connections because you're
modulating uh downstream um of course
neo course is not perfectly hierarchal
but things that are in general lower in
in the hierarchy would have lots of of
uh inputs from uh parts of the neoortex
that are higher in the hierarchy. That's
absolutely what we see. Um so yeah,
there's a lot of evidence uh that these
are two sides of the same coin um which
is there's some form of generative model
being implemented. I do think in AI one
way in which this manifests is the the
very clear success of self-s
supervision. I mean this idea although
the um actual predictive coding
algorithms that people have sort of
devised uh as the neo as uh neoortex
implementing when we've actually modeled
them they haven't outperformed any of
the stuff going on in in AI world the
principle of self-s supervision which is
can a system end up having really
interesting emergent properties and
generalize well when you only train it
on predicting sensory input that it
receives. Um and that clearly has become
the case. I mean if the transformer I
think is a great example of if you just
give it a bunch of data and you train it
through self-supervision i.e. masking so
you hide certain data inputs um it
becomes remarkably accurate and good at
generalizing across data that it hasn't
seen before which is in principle all a
gener what people are predicting or
claiming that the neoortex is doing as
generative model. Yeah, it it feels to
me that there is a bright difference
though between let's say a transformer
and and the neoortex. And I think the
difference is um maybe agency is not the
right word, but that you can think of
the the neurons I think as having some
kind of autonomy. So they're sending
messages to each other and then the
other, you know, it's eventually
consistent. So the other neuron will get
the message and it will decide itself
what it's going to do. and um in a
transformer just because of the way
they're connected and the backrop
algorithm and so on they they all um
they all kind of ride a Mexican wave
together to use an analogy. So it feels
like a difference in kind to me.
Well I mean clear clearly as I uh argue
in the book I don't think that the brain
is just one big transformer. So I would
agree with you in in the human brain
unless you think there's something
that's non-deterministic and sort of
magical happening. Uh you know I think
you would still say that there is either
uh you know base firing rates of neurons
uh that and then there's sensory input
that flows up and then goes through the
brain until eventually there's sort of
it's affecting uh muscles until you're
responding. So there is you know there
is sort of a deterministic flow
happening. it might not be as uh feed
forward as what's happening in
transformer which is definitely the
case. Um but they might both be sort of
uh you know deterministic in in a in a
similar fashion. I think a lot of people
I've had this exact sort of argument
with a lot of people and one
counterargument that people have towards
this idea um I don't know if I fully
agree with it but it's interesting is
that attention heads uh really are doing
something more magical than we give them
credit for which is they are kind of
dynamically rerouting and effectively
resetting the network um based on the
context that the prompt is getting. And
so although technically it's just a
series of you know matrix
multiplications etc. Um, if in principle
what's happening is these attention
heads are doing something really clever
where they're looking at the context of
a prompt and then effectively
dynamically reweing the network to
decide what it cares about and what it
doesn't. So there are people that think,
you know, there is something really
interesting happening in the transformer
that might be analogous to certain
things that are happening in the brain.
Um, but yeah, clearly, you know, these
these feed forward networks are are not
capturing everything that's going on in
the brain. Yeah, it's really interesting
what you said because the way I read
that is um things like chatbt and
language models, they are entropy
smuggling or agency smuggling. So what
that means is they kind of just do what
you tell them to do and all of the kind
of um the agency. So my directedness
comes from me. So I give it a prompt, it
does the thing that I wanted it to do
and then the kind of the the mapping
that you were talking about, I interpret
that a bit like a database query. So you
know depending on the prompt you give it
it'll activate a certain part of the
representation space and it will give
you a certain result back. But the the
the brain has this thing where all of
the neurons have their own directedness
and and the weird thing is at the cosmic
scale um agency is it seems to emerge.
So even transformer models that were
acting autonomously could presumably in
large enough scale give rise to
something that we think of as
directedness or goals or purpose or or
whatever. But it's almost like um in the
natural world because there are so many
levels, scales and scales of independent
autonomous things just kind of mingling
with each other independently and then
like downstream mixing their information
together and rinsing and repeating over
many many different scales. That seems
to be the thing that gives rise to all
of these amazing things like agency and
creativity and and etc.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, I mean I think the the
notion of agency is an interesting one
where um I really am amenable. I mean
there is sort of a a I don't know if I
would call it a schism in the field but
there are there are there is a debate
where uh between sort of the
reinforcement learning world and the
active inference world where um how much
of intelligence can be conceived as
optimizing a reward function um and sort
of the re the hardcore reinforcement
learning world is like everything is
just a reward and then the active
inference world is you know would argue
that not all behavior is driven just by
optimizing a single reward function.
There is some uncertainty minimization.
Um there is uh trying to satisfy your
own model of yourself, fulfill your own
predictions. These sort of things that
seem very well aligned to behavior we
see. But uh you know it's unclear which
of these is right. It's probably some
balance of the two. But to me agency
people would conceive of agency
differently in these two worlds, right?
So I think uh some people in the RL
world would say agency is just you give
something a reward function and then it
just learns over time try and optimize
that reward. Um in the more active
inference world which I do think has
legs and I'm obviously amendable to um
the idea of agency is a little bit more.
It's building a model of yourself um and
trying to infer what your goals are um
based on observing yourself and then
trying to make predictions to fulfill
those end goals. In other words, it's
constructed. Goals are constructed. And
this is sort of one of my favorite
Fristen papers uh is predictions not
commands. I don't know if you've read
that paper, but I think it's a brilliant
paper um about how you could reconceive
motor cortex not as sending motor
commands to your body, but actually as
building a model of yourself and
predicting what what will happen. And
the way the spinal cord is wired is it
just fulfills those predictions. Um, and
I think that's a really interesting uh
sort of reframe of how you could get
agency and really interesting smart
behavior in the absence of just a strict
reward function, right? So, how that
would learn is it's trying to model um
the behaviors it observes and then it's
trying to sort of predict those and
fulfill them. Um, so but yeah, I yeah, I
think agency is a really interesting
concept because it sort of manifests
itself in these different paradigms in
different ways. Yeah, I I find it
fascinating. I mean, um because the way
I read it in active inference
literature, it's a very principled
definition of an agent and there's still
a bit of a gap because I think Friston
would argue well in the natural world
because of the the laws of physics and
particles and and whatnot, you get the
emergence of things and things become
agents when they have a certain, you
know, um depth of planning, should we
say. Yep. But um yeah, it's it's really
really interesting and I guess he would
argue that you get all of these um
phenomena that give rise to agency like
biotic self-organization and and so on.
But um yeah, maybe we should do we we'll
slowly go go in that direction. So you
you give the example of um mice doing
planning.
Can you can you sketch that out?
>> Yeah. So this is another real like area
of neuroscience research that I just
absolutely love. Um so it was the case I
think it was the 40s or 50s I forget the
exact decade uh where Tolman observed
that worms when they uh uh mice when
they would reach choice points in mazes
where he was training them to navigate
around mazes would pause and then they
would sniff back and forth and then they
would choose an action. And so he
hypothesized this idea that uh they must
be engaging in vi in uh vicarious trial
and error. They must be imagining
possible outcomes before deciding. And
of course this was hugely controversial
um because there's no evidence. He had
no evidence that they were in fact
imagining anything. And of course most
people like to in the absence of
evidence assume animals are as dumb as
possible. Only when there's irrefutable
evidence will we imbue them with any
intellectual capacities which I think
isn't interesting human bias but that's
fine. Um and then uh David Reddish uh
who is also a close friend and mentor of
mine uh he did some amazing research uh
with some one of his PhD students. um
where they were recording hippocample
play cells. So it's very quick
background for for viewers. Um you can
go into the hippocampus of really any
mammal, but this is best well studied in
rats. And part of their hippocampus
region called CA1 has these things
called play cells. And so if you look at
if you record it as a mouse is moving
around a maze, what you find is this
incredible thing where there are neurons
that activate only in specific locations
in that two-dimensional plane. Um and
it's not based on how they got there. It
is egocentric is independent of their
egocentric path. It is alocentric
meaning in this in the plane of external
space. So they can come back to the same
place from any route and that same play
cell will activate. And as an aside um
from the evolutionary story, we find
similar types of cells. It's not exactly
as accurate, but we find similar types
of cells in fish in in the homologous
region of the hippocampus um of their
cortex where they have uh place-like
cells. It's not as accurate, but cells
that activate in certain locations in a
maze. What he found is when mice engage
in this act of vicarious trial and
error, meaning when they pause and look
back and forth, the place cells in the
hippocampus cease to only activate in
the location they are, it actually
starts activating down the paths of each
route it might take. In other words, you
can literally watch rats imagining the
future. One of the most inc I think one
of the most incredible neuroscience
findings. Um, and so he then took this
and then did a bunch of other
experiments which I think reveal even
further the power of sort of imagination
in in rats. One of my favorites is his
counterfactual learning studies where he
puts rats in this thing called
restaurant row where it's a sort of uh
square like Yeah, exactly. It's this
like a square like maze and as the rat
is going uh counterclockwise at each
sort of door a sound is released or made
and that sound signals to the rat
whether or not they can go right through
the door and get food in like I think
it's like 3 seconds or they're going to
have to wait 45 seconds before they get
the food and they're given a bunch of
time to try and get as much food as they
want. Rats have clear preferences. So,
some rats will really prefer bananas and
they don't really like the bland food.
So, what happens? Well, this presents a
set of irreversible choices to a rat.
So, let's say they come up and they can
either get uh they can either get a
treat uh right now. They can they can
get a treat right now that they don't
really like that much. Let's say it's
the bland treat or they can go to the
next one and hope that they're going to
get the banana really fast. If they go
to the next one and the banana sound is
long, meaning 45 seconds, then they
regret their choice because it would
have been better if they just went in
and quickly got the food. How do we know
they're regretting the choice? We can
literally watch them imagining eating
the foregone choice. We can go in a part
of their brain called the orbital
frontal cortex, which activates for
certain types of tastence, and we know
we can see them imagining the foregone
choice, and they end up making different
choices the next time around. They end
up being less likely to forego that that
choice in the future. So I think this is
just such an incredible finding of what
we mean when we say model based
reinforcement learning is clearly in
happening in these brains uh of very
very simple mammals.
>> There's a real challenge knowing which
simulations to run because if you think
about it we've got a search problem,
right? There's an intractable number of
simulations to run. So how do we how do
we fix that in AI and how do humans fix
that?
So, so this is one of the I think of the
many but this is one of the big
outstanding questions in AI which is how
do you effectively prune the search
space? We do not know how mammal brains
do this so well. So I can I'll give you
some like highle ideas or theories but
we we just don't know and this is one of
the big possible breakthroughs um in
figuring out you know how how do mammal
brains do such a good job of this. So
the thing that AlphaGo does which I
think perhaps is a clue um and is clever
is the selection of the search space
actually is bootstrapped on the temporal
difference learning model under the
hood. So this is actually very clever
which is let's say you train something
to uh learn without a model of the
world. All it's doing is it gets sensory
stimuli. It gets a model of a go board
and then it just predicts the right next
action. It just has a policy value
function that bootstraps on each other
etc. So no planning. If you want to add
planning to that, um, what they did,
which is quite brilliant, is you say,
okay, well, you know what? Instead of
building some other system to try and
choose good trajectories, why don't we
just use the the policy network and we
just don't only pick the first one, we
pick its favorite move, but then we also
look at what's your second favorite
move, your third favorite move, and
maybe your fourth favorite move. And
then let's literally play the games out.
Um, and let's just see let's play a
bunch of games against ourselves and
then see the ratios in which we win one
of them. And then what we might learn is
your second best guess was actually
better than your first best guess. But
we're not starting from every possible
possibility. We're saying let's
bootstrap on our best guesses of good
moves, but then check them by playing
out the possible futures. So if we were
to analogize that to the brain, what
that would suggest is perhaps it's the
basil ganglia, which a lot of evidence
suggests is engaging in this type of
sort of model free reinforcement
learning actually is the thing that
chooses the moves, but there's some
other system that lets us choose the
second best move, the third best move,
etc. Um, one way this might happen,
there's some evidence for this, far from
conclusive, that there's some notion of
uncertainty that frontal cortex or basil
ganglia is measuring and when the level
of uncertainty between the next actions
uh passes a threshold, pausing occurs.
Um, because when we see animals do this
vicarious trial and error, it almost
always occurs in moments of high
uncertainty when contingencies have
changed, when the right answer is not
obvious. Um, and so you could conceive
of this as a policy network where you're
evaluating its best choice, second best
choice, third best choice. And when
there's uncertainty about it, in other
words, they're close together or um,
there's some other measure of
uncertainty. Perhaps you have parallel
policy models that and you're comparing
the similarity between them. A lot of
different ways to do this. Um, that
triggers a process of playing forward.
This is another key thing that mammal
brains do that AlphaGo does not do. Alph
Go engage in planning on every move. So
there was never the question of when do
we pause to plan in a game of go it
doesn't matter just engage in planning
in every move because we can do it so
fast in the real world there's so much
uncertainty and noise um and we need to
be so energy efficient with human brains
we can't engage in planning every
instant so we need some mechanism that
tells us when to stop and think about
what I'm going to do next and when I can
just continuously go with model free
choice. This is also something we don't
know how mammal brains do. Um but I
think you know a reasonable uh sort of
speculation is that there's some
uncertainty measurement that's
occurring. One last point I'll make that
I think parallels in an interesting way
to some of Hawkins ideas um and FO's
ideas is if you take the thousand brains
uh model and you apply it to frontal
cortex in other words we have multiple
parallel models of ourselves. Um you
could imagine that there's an
uncertainty measurement the same way we
do uncertainty measurement uh in a lot
of deep learning models where you create
parallel models and you just measure how
similar are the predictions of the model
and if multiple parallel models predict
similar things we just measure it as low
uncertainty. When they diverge
substantially all of a sudden we measure
high uncertainty. So again speculation
but you could imagine if it is the case
we have redundant models in the
neoortex. Then might it be the case that
somewhere perhaps the phalamus or the
basil ganglia the the similarity or
differences between these predictions
are a measure of uncertainty that
triggers pausing. Um Steven Gber has
similar ideas. He calls this like
matching and non-matching. Um
>> yeah yeah yeah
>> yeah like almost because um our ability
to do abduction is something that
fascinates me and there is some kind of
a model selection or or or matching um
step that that goes on there but um
anyway so so we we've got the neoortex
it's an absolute beast when it comes to
predicting sensory signals and then we
we see the the emergence of planning and
and also smart planning as as we've just
spoken about. So now we're actually
talking about traversing these sensory
networks over space and time. And then
something else really interesting
happens. So the the next two moves you
make are bringing in um selfhood. So
like you know bringing yourself as an
explicit actor and including that in the
planning and and then that naturally
leads to this idea of I would call it
teology but you know um why or
intentionality.
So let's let's go on that journey. So
maybe the the the self-modeling first.
How does that come into the picture?
>> Um so I think there's two notions of
selfmodeling. Um one notion of
self-modeling is the kind that I think
we see in um early mammals. And this is
an idea where um the frontal cortex of
mammals uh region uh in general called a
granular prefrontal cortex which is
present in all mammals and largely
believed to have existed in the very
first mammal brains um gets sensory
input from um an animal's own in uh
introspective signals. So interceptive
signals. So uh it gets input from the
hypothalamus which measures things like
hunger. Um um it gets input from uh
amydala which measures things like
veilance in the world uh fear uh danger
etc. um and when uh does the arranular
prefrontal cortex get most excited? It's
in these moments of uncertainty and in
these moments where they're engaging in
planning and episodic memory. Um and if
you damage uh a granular prefrontal
cortex in rats uh they seem to
dramatically have impaired if if not
completely lose the ability to engage in
mental stimulation, episodic memory,
etc. Okay. So I think what one might uh
speculate is happening here which I
don't is not a novel suggestion by me is
it's modeling the self um uh in other
words modeling what is the activations
of uh the amygdala and the hypothalammus
that are happening and why am I doing
what I'm doing. In other words, if I
wake up and I see I have these
hypothalammic activations and then I go
down to to go get water, um, then it
builds a model of in the presence of
these hypothalammic activations, the
next action is I'm going to go over and
get water, which and it constructs an
explanation. And so, as as odd and
philosophical as that sounds, that is in
principle computationally exactly the
same thing as when we showed a picture
of that triangle and your posterior
sensory cortex construct an explanation
of what it saw. I I perceive the
triangle. So this idea of constructing
an explanation of one's own behavior is
this idea of the first idea of self um
which is uh constructing intent. And
there's lots of evidence that even in
rats if you record neurons in their
arranular prefrontal cortex and they
seem to be very sensitive to tasks that
they're in and measuring progress
towards goals, there's lots of evidence
that it's doing something something akin
to that. So that's one notion of of
self. When you get to primates, you see
a whole new region of uh frontal cortex
emerge. Uh what's called granular
prefrontal cortex, which is only seen in
the primate lineage. There's no other uh
mammals that have this region of
prefrontal cortex. Um as a quick aside
for anyone who's interested, the reason
it's called granular versus a granular
is most neoortex has six layers. The
fourth layer is called the granle layer
because it contains granle cells, just a
certain type of neuron. And for a
variety of really unknown reasons, but
there's some interesting speculations.
Um, a granular prefrontal cortex is
missing layer four. Um, and that's why
it's called a granular. Same thing with
motor cortex is missing layer 4. So most
mammals their front whole frontal cortex
is missing layer a fourth layer. It only
has five layers. But in primates, you
get this granular prefrontal cortex.
This huge region of neoortex that does
contain a layer 4. And the best
explanation for this I've actually seen
Fristristen talk about. I'm happy to go
into it if you think you're folks would
be listen interested in it. But the
point is there's a new Do you want to go
me to go into that?
>> Oh. Oh yeah. Yeah. I mean so we we love
Friston and I mean because active
inference is actually about preferences.
It's you know because an agent expresses
agency by um kind of like adapting the
environment to suit its preferences or
to kind of make the environment like its
preferences. So basically this is a a
theory of valition [snorts]
right and and act you know what what
Carl Fritz's talking about is where do
these goals come from? Where does the
valition come from? And and you spoke
with Carl about that I think over
several years didn't you?
>> Yep. Yep. Yeah. Carl's been a wonderful
mentor of mine. Um I honestly like it's
a funny story. I like won I didn't know
this was a term in academia but there's
the the reviewer lottery where you just
get lucky and you get a reviewer. for
the first paper I submitted, uh, Carl
Fen was a reviewer on, which I was just
lucky, and then he became a mentor and
and reviewed my book and gave me lots of
good feedback. So, yeah, he's an
amazing, uh, person, been a wonderful
mentor of mine. Um, so, yes. So, okay,
so let's talk about granular versus a
granular because I think the best theory
I've seen is Fristen's theory on this.
So, what does layer 4 do in neoortex?
Across the entire neoortex, layer 4 is
where sensory input is received. the
primary sensory input is received into
the neoccortical column. Um this comes
from the phalamus. So the canonical
model is sensory input from sensors,
eyes, ears, uh skin flows up through the
brain stem to the phalamus. Uh and then
from the phalamus propagates to layer 4
and then from layer 4 it goes within the
variety of other layers of neoortex. So
um and then other layers of neoortex
project back to the the rest of the
brain. So why would it be the case that
regions of neoortex would not have a
layer 4? Well, if you actually watch an
animal's development, what's interesting
is mammals with a a granular prefrontal
cortex, it's not always a granular. It
actually starts having a layer 4 and the
layer 4 atrophies over development. And
so I think this is very uh and mirrors
well for's idea of active inference
where what's happening is the
neoccortical column can kind of be in
two phases. It can either be trying to
match its model of the world to its
sensory input. In other words, I see
sensory input and I'm trying to infer
what's there and I'm going to construct
the idea of a triangle. But there's
another state of of a neocortical column
which is generation which is I'm going
to start from the latent representation
of a triangle. I'm going to imagine and
explore it. And so one idea is that what
frontal cortex does is primarily try and
fit the world to its model. In other
words, it spends the vast majority of
its time constructing intent and not
trying to modify that intent to fit what
it observes, but in fact try to change
what an animal does to satisfy its
intent. So it's so layer 4 atrophies.
Doesn't actually go all the way. If you
go deep into a brain, you see some basic
layer four. So it's not completely gone,
but it atrophies because frontal cortex
spends very little time trying to change
what it perceives its intent to be to
map what the animal's doing. But in
fact, what it does, it tries to change
what an animal does to map it match to
its intent. And what I think is so
interesting and brilliant about this
idea is it explains exactly why layer 4
doesn't start not existing. Because at
first, an animal needs to build a model
of itself. Thus, layer 4 is present. But
over time it shifts towards once I have
a model of what I want and who I am and
the things I would do, I don't need to
spend as much time changing my model of
self, um I'm going to spend most of my
time trying to change my behavior. Um so
this is very a very speculative idea,
but it makes a lot of sense uh in the
context of active inference. Um and it's
the best to personally and all the my
reading of uh explanations of why uh a
granularity exists the best explanation
I've seen.
>> Yeah. So, so this is absolutely
fascinating and in my mind it bridges
the gap between internalism and
externalism because he's describing this
kind of didactic exchange to use the you
know there are certain high entropy
words that only Friston uses. So if I
say didactic exchange you know and by
the way if you if you just for the folks
at home if you read Friston's papers
there are certain words so he says this
licenses something. So, you know, if you
see the word licenses, then Friston
wrote the paper. But anyway, [laughter]
um but but yeah, so but you you um you
have this kind of like um you know, like
the agents have models of the world, but
they're they're kind of exchanging
information with with the other agents
and then you get what what an an agent
does is it has this generative model of
policies, you know, which is just a
sequence of of actions. And here's where
I want to get into the the nitty-gritty
a tiny bit. So you could think of those
um those those plans as being goals. So
you can think of a goal as just being an
end state in one of your plans. But that
doesn't really satisfy me because I
think of goals like eating food as being
like a kind of a category not not like a
kind of a pointalistic traversal of you
know a specific state in the future
because it kind of feels like well if
there's an infinite number of goals then
in some sense there are no goals at all.
So what is a goal to you?
>> So okay so great question. So I think
this is where um semantics matters a
lot. I think we can think about goals in
several ways. So I think if we think
strict RL lands um they would just think
about goals as you're just optimizing a
reward function. What the goal the goal
is simple. There's only one goal which
is maximize reward. And in a changing
complex world your reward function might
fluctuate over time um etc etc but the
goal is is singular. In the active
inference world, what I find compelling
is it introduces a uh a different
component of what we mean by a goal. Um,
which has not is not just sort of a
intellectual you know of intellectual
interest just because it's uh cool but
has like very real AI implications
actually because it contains the notion
of explanability. So, for example, um if
I am imagining go if I'm if I wake up
and I'm hungry and I start imagining
ways to satiate my hunger and then I
decide I'm going to get in a car and I'm
going to go uh to this restaurant and
then I'm going to go eat this specific
food. When I get into the car and
someone calls me and go, "Why'd you get
in the car?"
The reason I can explain that so easily
is because there was a rendered
simulation of a plan that terminated an
end state that I deemed that I wanted I
selected. So it's very easy to explain
why I did that. Um, in the absence of
that, it's actually very hard to explain
why you're doing things. If you're
walking down the street, if I asked you
to explain any one of your model free
behaviors, why did you move your foot
there instead of there? You have no
explanation. Um, and so I think you can
think about you can assign the word
goals to multiple levels here. Um, I
think you could say it's terminating the
end state. You could say the goal is
some more abstract representation of the
satiation of thirst in general. Um, and
you could think about that as distinct
from just the reward function. Some
might challenge that and just say, well,
all that you're talking about then is
just optimize reward function. But I
think you could make an argument that
there is a distinction happening there.
Um, but what I what I think is so
critical that's unique that happens
within mammal brains. It's why I was
sort of really honing in on that is the
ability to plan a series of actions that
terminates an end result and then
execute those that that plan. And I
think that has very clear implications
for explanability
um which sort of model free actions do
not. But but yeah, so that would be how
I would think about goals. But I think
it is a little bit of a semantic where
we can think about the the concept of
goals in multiple ways. How do we
actually know what the cognitive
abilities were of early animals and and
why should we care?
Great question. Um, so I think there's
two reasons why we should care about the
evolution of our brains and
intelligence. The first is to understand
who we are. So the the scope of what it
means to be a human is not constrained
to what it means to be a homo sapiens.
So so much ink has been spilled on the
last 70,000 years of us being homo
sapiens. But if aliens were to come down
and engage with us and analyze us as a
species, most of the things they would
observe about us don't come from our
legacy as homo sapiens. They come from
our legacy of being a primate and our
legacy of being a mammal and our legacy
of being a vertebrate and our legacy of
being an animal in general. And so I
think if we want to understand what it
means to be a human being, I I don't
think we can skip the full 600
millionyear story of how we came to be.
Um, and I think in there is so much rich
history and insight about what it means
to be us. So I think that's one really
key reason. It's it's our it's our
legacy. It's our history. Um, how we
came to be. The second perhaps more
practical reason is I think
understanding the evolution of the human
brain and the evolution of human
intelligence is a key tool in our
toolbox to understanding how the brain
works and how human intelligence works.
It's by no means the only method. It
might not even be the main method, but
it's a very useful method to add to the
toolbox. So the problem with going into
the human brain and trying to directly
reverse engineer it is that evolution
doesn't work in clean ways. It doesn't
work the way a human designer would. it
doesn't work from first principles. It
tinkers. And so when we go into the
brain, we see all of this messiness.
There's redundant systems. There's
vestigial systems. Um, you know, new
things evolve that make old things
redundant, but they're still there. Um,
lots of processing is duplicated in
different regions. And so, um, one way
to understand the brain is to
continuously probe it as the human brain
is, which is fine. But another method
that's also useful and can impose
constraints for us is to actually track
the history of how it came to be. And
that can provide insights as to uh when
this brain modification occurred such as
when the neoortex evolved um or uh when
the basil ganglia evolved um what were
the new abilities that this enabled um
and how did it affect the prior brain
regions that were already there and so
this can give us insight into how the
brain works today. So I think in the
toolbox that we have of ways to reverse
engineer the brain, I think this is just
an underappreciated one um that is
worthy of being included. Um and of
course understanding how the human brain
works has so many different
applications. Helps us with mental
health, helps us with understanding why
people do what we do. Um it helps us
with um building AI systems. Um I think
there's lots of insights to garner for
the brain. So that's that's why to do
it. Now, how to reverse engineer what
behavioral abilities exist in our
ancestors is a really interesting
question. Um, of course, we can't go
back in time. Um, so, so what we can do
though, um, is there are there are
mechanisms to reverse engineer what
their brains looked like and there are
abilities they had. So, what their
brains looked like we can do just by
looking at other animals in the animal
kingdom. So for example, we can look at
all of the existing primates and all of
the existing non- primite mammals and we
can see what are the common brain
structures that exist between them. We
can look at genetic analysis meaning
what things seem to derive from similar
roots and we can back into what do we
what seems to be common and shared
amongst them and thus what do we think
was actually existing in the brains of
the first mammals. We do the same thing
with fish and reptiles to do that uh
with early vertebrates and we can do
that with invertebrates to try and infer
what was existing in the first
bilaterians. In other words, the first
animal with brains. Um so we can compare
different brains to try and back into
what the brains looked like for
behavioral abilities. There are sort of
three ways you do this and you need this
is like my uh sort of approach to trying
to infer behavioral abilities. I call
them the in-roup condition, the outgroup
condition and the stem group condition.
So in order to make the argument that a
behavioral ability emerged at a certain
location in our evolutionary history. So
for example a behavioral ability like
episodic memory evolving with the first
mammals. You need to satisfy these three
criteria. The ingroup condition
stipulates that most ancestors or sorry
most descendants of this species in
other words most mammals should show
this ability. Doesn't mean all of them.
Abilities get lost all the time but most
of them should show this ability. And
the neural mechanisms by which the
ability comes uh emerges should come
from homologous regions. What that means
is a shared neural underpinning. So if
for example mammals show episodic memory
but they come from uh neurological
regions that independently evolved along
different mammal lineages and that
suggests it wasn't present in the first
mammals. But if they all emerge from
regions that emerged with early mammals
that's good evidence that this ability
also emerged with mammals. The out group
condition says most doesn't have to be
all but at least many non-mamal so out
group non-mamal vertebrates um so so the
group right above should not show this
ability and if they do show the ability
it should emerge from non-homologous
regions in other words parts of their
brain that evolved independently. So for
example, birds definitely show episotic
memory. Um but when we look into the uh
the brain regions from which episotic
memory emerges, it's clearly
non-homologous. It's a part of the brain
that mammals the early vertebrates did
not have. And the stem group condition
is in the ecological sort of dynamics
that early mammals existed or this this
ancestor existed. It we should be able
to devise an argument for why this
ability would have been adaptive. So why
would episodic memory have evolved? So
with these three things, we can start to
infer the story of when behavioral
abilities emerged. Is this perfect?
Absolutely not. Um because we do not
have uh enough we do not have a ton of
data on behavioral abilities across
species. So as new evidence emerges, the
story might change. Um but with these
three conditions, we can do a reasonable
job inferring what abilities emerged.
And the main finding of the book which
uh or the research which led me to be so
excited about the book is when you do
this what's kind of crazy is you find a
a re as a first approximation a really
coherent story which is a lot of the
behavioral abilities that emerge at each
milestone in brain evolution don't seem
to be sort of a haphazard array of
different skills but often emerge from
really one what I call breakthrough but
one underlying intellectual capacity
applied in different ways. Um so so
that's sort of the idea of the five
breakthroughs. One thing to note
actually about the basil ganglia is I
think this is a little bit of a sidebar
but I think fun. Um the basil ganglia I
think is one of the most
underappreciated parts of the brain. Uh
in the sense that so much work has gone
into understanding how the neoortex
functions. So much work has gone into
the neoccortical column and that's all
wonderful work to be done. But the basil
ganglia um not only is evolutionarily
much older. If you look in a lamprey
fish, as we talked about I think last
time um a lampray fish has a common
ancestor with us 500 million years ago.
Um it's one of the most uh distant
vertebrae cousins that still exists
today. They have a basil ganglia looks
exactly like our basil ganglia. Um same
inner structure and the basil ganglia
has perhaps one of the most beautiful
internal structures that can be
computationally reverse engineered. um
there's not good uh consensus on the
actual inner wiring and the computations
performed by a neoccortical column but
there is much broader consensus as to
what's being executed by uh the basal
ganglia and without getting overly
technical and uh perhaps boring people
um I would encourage anyone who's
computationally interested in this to
dive into the literature here because it
is it is almost beautiful that evolution
came up with this for example the the
input structure of the basil ganglia
has this mosaic of neurons that each
express two different types of dopamine
receptors. This would be my own little
technical diet tribe. One are called D1
receptors and then there are D2
receptors.
D1 receptors when it receives dopamine
strengthens connections. D2 receptors
when they lose dopamine strengthen
connections. And now you track these
different uh neurons and they actually
split their paths. The D1 receptors go
to a nuclei that when activated um
disinhibits behaviors and D2 neurons go
through a different set of nuclei that
when activated inhibits behaviors. And
so we can literally watch how dopamine
signals drive repeated behavior and
inhibit and dopamine drops inhibits
behavior. We can literally look at the
mosaic of of connectivity here and say,
"Oh, when you spike dopamine, it weakens
the stop pathway which through D2
neurons and it and it disinhibits the go
pathway through D1 neurons and makes you
more likely to repeat the behavior and
vice versa if something bad happens and
you lose dopamine." And I think that is
just so beautiful um that evolution
stumbled on something that uh that clean
um uh in its macro structure. So just
diet tribe on I I think the basil
ganglia is cool.
>> Yeah, it's quite interesting as well.
You know, people get addicted to drugs.
A lot of that is about wire heading in
the basil ganglia. And um Yep. And and
of course um habitual learning is
something that you know when when
something becomes so habituated it kind
of you know just moves down the stack
into the basil ganglia and and you know
so drug taking would be an example of
that. And you actually cited I think an
experiment in China where they removed
part of the basil ganglia and and there
was a 40% um recidivism from uh
addiction.
>> Yeah, very controversial study that
probably uh violates many ethical codes
in the US. But yes, they did this study
for um intractable heroin addiction um
and they lesioned a part of the basil
ganglia called the nucleus encumbent um
which uh is sort of where goals are
habitually selected um and uh it showed
a dramatic reduction in heroin
addiction. Also had other sort of side
effects that maybe doctors would deem uh
unreasonable um but it def it worked um
and it absolutely reduced sort of the
addictive cravings that are triggered by
stimuli.
>> Yeah. the the the story of this chapter,
incredible chapter. I've just I've just
been studying it today in great detail,
is the story of mentalizing, but I I
would I would call it um you know,
social complexification. Actually,
that's a hypothesis of why our brains
expanded so dramatically. So, there was
this extinction event. I think it was at
the the Deavonian extinction events and
only birds and you know not many things
survived and then um we got the chance
to kind of evolve after that and and our
brains rapidly exploded and there are
different theories about why that
happened. You know maybe it was because
we had access to loads of calories in
the form of fruit um preferential access
and it gave us an incredible amount of
um time and energy the excess of which
might have led to social
complexification. Can can you just sort
of give us a little bit of a background
about that first piece um first?
>> Absolutely. So, um we don't know there's
lots of speculations, but we don't know
why this occurred with primates, but we
do have um some really good evidence
that at least part of what drove the
sort of explosion in primate brains was
social dynamics. Um and so Robin Dunbar
did sort of the the seinal work here
where what he showed is in primates the
encphilization quotient which is just
the ratio uh like brain size especially
the neocortical ratio so the ratio of
the size of the neoortex to the rest of
the brain is extremely correlated with
social group size in primates. So the
bigger a social group size you find in a
group of primates, the bigger their
neoortex seems to be relative to the the
their their body size. And what's so
interesting is you don't see this in
most other mammals. So this is not a
standard correlation that applies across
the animal kingdom. It seems to be this
correlation that's very specific um to
primates. There might be other mammals,
but for most mammals, you don't see this
correlation. And so, uh, Robin Dunar's
famous social brain hypothesis is what
drove the explosion in primate brains,
um, is some form of social dynamic
between people. Um, and the more social
relationships you're managing, the
bigger your brain has to be. Now, that
doesn't explain what specifically
happened in the brain, which is what we
can get to with mentalizing and why that
applies. Um, but it does suggest that
whatever drove this explosion in brain
size, um, seems to be something
correlated to social grouping. And
what's interesting about primate social
groups relative to not all mammals but
many other mammals is they're very very
political. So so many mammals live in uh
sort of solitary uh sort of social lives
where uh the males mostly live alone um
and females will rear a child and then
usually they'll go off on their own.
There are there are animals that live in
uh sort of herds where they they
socially group together but there's not
really very rigorous sort of hierarchies
amongst them. Um but primates especially
apes have these really complicated
social structures with rigid
hierarchies. Um so there there truly is
someone at the top of the hierarchy and
we can measure this through you know
primatologists have gone to painstaking
lengths to verify this. For example
there's transitivity. So if you show
that one primate tends to show a
submissive signal to another primate um
and that other primate shows a
submissive signal to another one then
it's almost definitely the case that
that first one will show a submissive
signal to the last one. Um in other
words these these are real rigid
hierarchies are not like random
interactions of submission and
dominance. And um and what we see is one
of the main ways uh you survive as a
primate is you you successfully climb
this hierarchy. Um, and so what's so
interesting is in many mammals, what
makes someone the top dog or the sort of
person who's the top of a hierarchy is
is sort of bronze. It's just strength.
They're just show they're trying to
flaunt who would win in a physical
altercation, which evolutionarily is
beneficial because if you can prevent
actually fighting each other and just
say this is what who would win the
fight, then we both save energy just
having these sort of fake battles and
then I can if if whoever wins gets to
eat the food, etc. But with primates,
it's not always the strongest one that
reaches the top. It's the most socially
savvy one. And socially savviness comes
into uh um these alliances that are
built within primates. So you'll see
that people at the top of the hierarchy
frequently will befriend and groom and
come to the aid of certain uh other
non-family members. And those folks will
thus reciprocate and come to their aid.
And there are these really interesting
dynamics that play out. Um you even see
wars. So there's mutinies that take
place in primate societies. Um so so in
this sort of soup of uh the way to
survive and get evolutionary advantage
as a primate is not perhaps only to make
sure you get access to food. But to
climb a social hierarchy, all of a
sudden there are these huge social
pressures to be able to do things like
infer what someone else would do in a
certain circumstance or what someone
knows or what you can get away with or
how to change someone's opinion of you.
Um, and so and so what that, you know,
lines nicely to is what we see of the
new brain regions that emerged in
primates. most notably is brain region
called the granular prefrontal cortex
and these areas in the back of the brain
called the superior temporal sulcus
temporal parietal junction. These brain
regions across primates are highly
implicated uh in what I call mentalizing
um uh which is thinking about thinking
um but the the standard literature would
call this just theory of mind. Um, so
being able to infer the intent or
knowledge of someone else. And so it's
very it's easy to understand why this
would be so adaptively valuable in a
sort of politicking arms race um where
you're trying to sort of deceive each
other. There's a great study um that
really revealed this with primates by
Emil Mensel um in the 1970s and I love
this this story. So he was trying to he
was he had this like oneacre forest. Do
you want to ask a question or
>> are you going to do the Machavelian
apes?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. God. [laughter]
>> Okay. Okay. Um so Emil Mensel had this
1acre forest um and his main objective
was not to study uh uh ape social
behaviors um in the sense of how they
would sort of climb social hierarchies.
His only objective was to measure
spatial reasoning in chimpanzees. Um and
so he had this group of of chimps. There
was one chimp named Belle, another one
named Rock, and there was a few others.
and he would show Belle the location of
food. So he would hide food under a bush
and then he would see would Belle go
back to that same location looking for
food. In other words, could she remember
locations in in 3D space or or
two-dimensional map-like space? And what
he found is readily yes, they do that.
And you know, we now know that lots of
mammals are capable of that. In fact,
even fish can do things like that. But
in this study, he started finding
something that was odd. Um, when Belle
would find the food, what she would
frequently do is share it with her
fellow uh, chimpanzeee group members.
Um, and that was great until Rock, who
was a high sort of ranking aggressive
male, when she would share, would take
the food from her.
And so what she started doing is hiding
the food when she found it. So instead
of sharing with Rock, she would just sit
on the food. Um, and so Rock realized
she was doing this and not sharing. So
Rock would come over and push her to try
and get the food under her. So then what
she started doing was when she knew the
location of the food because on some
recurring cycle or experiment or signal
that the food was now available, what
she would do is not go to it until Rock
was not looking.
So then what did Rock start doing? Rock
started pretending not to look. Rock
would look away while uh Belle would go
towards the food. And once he noticed
she was doing that, he would turn around
and run to try and grab the food before
her. So then Belle started trying to
lead him in the wrong directions. And so
this this cycle of deception,
counterdeception kept playing out. And
what that becomes this beautiful
anecdote of is sort of a case study in
what happens when you have a bunch of
sort of hierarchically interacting um
animals in an arms race for things like
this. Um what you get is deception and
counterdeception. Um, and that's really
only conceivable with some notion of
theory of mind because in order for
Belle to trick or try to trick Rock, she
needs to be able to say that in order
for me to change the knowledge in Rock's
head of where the food is, what I need
to do is walk in this other direction.
And what that will do is make Rock think
the food is in this direction when in
fact I know it's in this other location.
Or also to reason about someone's
intentions. I know Rock intends to trick
me. So when he's looking away, I don't
believe that he in fact is not paying
attention. And so this was sort of one
of the first early anecdotes that some
form of theory of mind is is occurring
in primates. There has since been lots
of studies that show this. Um and so for
example, just to give some some case
studies here, you can take a chimpanzee
and you can teach them that uh in when
there's two boxes, the box with a red
mark on it is the one with food in it.
So they easily will learn that. Then
what you do is you have an experimentter
come in with two boxes and they bend
over and they mark one and then they
accidentally they pretend to
accidentally drop the marker on the
other and then they leave. So the
marking is identical in both cases. The
chimpanzees always go for the one that
was intentionally marked. They can infer
the difference between of the same
stimuli of someone meaning to do
something intending and something being
an accident. Um there's other studies of
uh chimpanzees playing with different
goggles. And so one goggle you can't see
through another goggle you can. And if
you put those goggles on human
experimenters, the chimpanzees always go
who have food. They always go to the
experimentter with the see-through
goggles asking for food. So they're
somehow inferring that the other person
can't see them. So why would they ask?
So there's lots of studies that show
this ability. And evidence outside of
primates and other mammals is very
loose. So it's inconclusive,
controversial, but the loose evidence
shows up in only the smartest mammals,
which possibly suggests some independent
convergence. So
>> yeah,
>> yeah, there's lots of rich evidence that
this theory of mind exists within
primates and it emerges from these
uniquely primate regions. Um, and I'm
happy to go into the evidence uh of
brains, but I'll stop there for a
second. So with the Machavelian apes,
the X-risk people, you know, there are
people who talk about AI killing
everyone and they make the argument um
it's called instrumental convergence
from Nick Bostonramm, which is basically
that, you know, things like power
seeking and deceptive behavior would be
instrumental to any end goal. And this
is a great example from the animal
kingdom of deceptive Machavelian
behavior. So I guess it does seem
plausible at least on the surface that
um a level of um you know let's say
sophisticated agents um following their
own intentions and inferring the
intentions of others would seek to
deceive each other. That's like a
natural phenomenon.
>> I absolutely think so. Um I absolutely
think it is is the case that uh if you
the more autonomy you give an
intelligent agent uh and the more
ability you give it to define its own
sub goals the more risk emerges um
because you absolutely get uh what Nick
Brm is talking about which is an a sub
goal to trying to help cure cancer might
be dominate all of earth and control the
labor supply and allocation of resources
amongst all of earth. So, but I don't
think that's necessarily inevitable. I
think it is a risk. Um, evolution is a
constrained search algorithm for uh
intelligent entities. It is not it does
not give moral weight to what emerges.
This is I think uh uh an important
distinction which is just because
something is a natural consequence of
evolutionary systems does not mean that
we should deem it morally superior.
>> Yeah, that's the naturalistic fallacy,
>> right? So it might be the case that it
is very likely if you that uh species
will eventually enter a politicking arms
race and certain forms of deception will
emerge and power seeking will emerge.
That doesn't mean when we produce our
own sort of intelligent entities in AI
that we should imbue them with that with
those features. One of the, I think,
optimistic outcomes of this new AI world
we're going to enter in the next hundred
years is that we actually now as
designers can do our best to try and
remove some of the evolutionary baggage
that we don't like that's that's evolved
in humans in these new entities. Um, and
so, um, there's of course risk. Um, but
I think there's also the a really great
opportunity that we could have
benevolent beings that uh do not seek to
dominate. Um, you know, Yan Lun talks a
lot a lot about this. Um, and um are
less selfish. Um and so so yeah, I think
there's a great opportunity, but there's
definitely risk because the second you
give an autonomous agent the opportunity
to produce its own sub goals, you need
to have really rich either constraints
or a really well- definfined reward
function um or uh you know one ability
that I think comes from mentalizing
actually is and this is an idea in
alignment research which is uh if you
can convince an AI agent to try and do
what it thinks the human wants it to
What you're actually doing is you're
requiring it to engage in some form of
mentalizing to infer the preferences of
the requesttor and then try and do what
is best for that for that individual
because you can't just have them take
requests at at face value because then
there's all these opportunities for
misinterpretations. The f you know Nick
Boston's famous paperclip factory
maximize production of paper clips earth
is turned into paper clips. We obviously
don't want that. But with mentalizing,
with the ability to model the internal
simulation of another mind and be able
to play out how would this person feel
about possible futures, um you could
imagine optimistically an outcome where
an AI agent could easily infer if I turn
all of Earth into paper clips, that's
not what the person giving me this
request would have in fact wanted. They
would regret that outcome. Um um so of
course it doesn't fully derisk things
but it is one methodology and one
learning from sort of uh evolutionary
neuroscience I think we can garner that
mentalizing is a tool that can be used
to try and stabilize
uh sort of uh requests that we give each
other in a more grounded way so there's
not these types of misinterpretations.
Of course caveat humans misinterpret
each other all the time. It's by no
means perfect. Um but it is a a tool
>> and and I think that's a very natural
phenomenon. I think any intelligence
system is naturally incoherent. I think
it's impossible to have a single
monolithic intelligence which is
monoomaniacally you know focused in in a
particular direction. But but anyway I
want to just slightly rewind a little
bit to what we were saying. So the the
first animals they um they had quite
simplistic um social games that they
were playing. So they were interested in
strength and submission and it was a
fairly fixed interface. And what was
really interesting is that deer, for
example, they lock horns, don't they? So
it's predictive. They don't actually
have to have a fight because that would
be, you know, evolutionary um
evolutionarily not a smart thing to do.
So um so the social game they play, even
though the game is fixed, it's
predictive, which is fascinating. And
then you were telling the story of I
think um uh monkeys and macaks how they
have this really interesting virtual
social game where strength and social
status diverged. So your social status
actually became this virtual thing that
was based on grooming and pruning and
lots of completely unrelated things. And
it was entirely possible for um a very
weak macac to have a significantly
higher social status than than a big um
strong one. So that's really
fascinating. But then we get into I mean
maybe a broader question is we are still
very social creatures ourselves. We have
um Facebook for example and could you
just arguably you know could you
cynically argue that Facebook or you
know all socializing is just a kind of
arms race to improve our social status.
So when we're kind of posting on
Facebook in a way it's like the deer
locking horns. It's us playing these
status games without having to have a
fight with each other.
I think uh there is an aspect of human
behavior that can absolutely be
explained by this. There's a great book
called um
uh the elephant in the brain.
>> Oh yes,
>> there's a great book called the elephant
in the brain.
>> Um that talks about uh how much of human
behavior can be explained by um this
sort of status seeking uh behavior. And
the reason why it's so hard to study is
because it's uh what they call, I think,
a cognitive taboo or an intellectual
taboo where we don't want to admit it to
ourselves. So, we self-dilute our um
ourselves into believing we're doing
things for virtuous reasons because it
makes it easy. It's more convincing. If
I know that I'm doing something to
deceive someone, it's easier to tell
that I'm doing it. If I genuinely
believe that I'm doing these things to
help the world, but subconsciously, of
course, they're actually just benefiting
me. it's more convincing to other
people. So their argument is primates
evolved this sort of selfdeceit um to
make them more convincing and this
really accelerated with language um and
humans and and all that. So I think it's
definitely it's very likely to be the
case that the the core thesis of their
book is right that a lot of human
behavior is this sort of subtle status
seeeking um which I do think has uh not
to go on a sort of tangent here but I do
think has sort of uh social political
theory implications here where um you
know how do we make sure that society
doesn't devolve into just a hedonic
treadmill where um you know the
interesting thing about social status is
it's always definitionally a scarce
resource um because it's just a ranking
game. So, so unlike physical resources
where it is possible for all of us to
live better um than kings did a thousand
years ago or kings or queens did a
thousand years ago, we can all have
better access to medical care, all
better access to information, um all
better access to food. Social status is
always a zero- sum game. um unless
someone can conceive of a better way to
to do it. But I think in most cases it's
a zero- sum game. And this is
problematic because if if over time most
of our actions become pursuing social
status, then we're going to forever be
in this sort of game. Now, I don't think
personally that we're doomed to this. I
think there are absolutely better
virtues in the human psychology where
not everything we do is based on
pursuing social status. Um, and I think
you can conceive of uh dynamics where
humans are doing things for other
reasons, not just to to gain status. Um,
but I think it's absolutely fair to say
that a surprising amount of human
behavior is status seeking and maybe a
depressing amount.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, um I I agree with you
and and I don't necessarily want to get
too philosophical on that, but yeah,
that that book was um will store status
games where he said that there were
three meta status games that we played.
I think he gave Yeah. the virtue game,
the dominance game, the success game.
So, you know, I might be playing the
success game. I want to have the best
podcast or or whatever. But, um, but no,
the the the reason I bring this up is
the difference between humans and
animals is they're just playing one
game. So, it's really interesting that
they have this mimemetic social score,
but the the game is the same everywhere,
whereas for us, we go one level of
abstraction up. So, the success game to
us can be manifest in in a myriad of
different ways. It could be successful
at playing computer games. It could be,
you know, writing books or or making
podcasts or whatever. So, it's almost
like we we fractionate our our social
ranking into a myriad of different
games. And I think that's a little bit
of a testament to the difference us
humans have in general with our meta
cognition, which is our ability to kind
of like create the mometics, you know,
um in a novel way.
One thing that I've that's sort of
related to this um at least in early
human societies
is one way to sort of I'm taking a
little bit from the business world here
um where one way to reduce sort of
status infighting is to make it such
that members of a team have distinct
roles and I don't think this lesson only
comes from management theory and you
know entrepreneurship I think this
probably derives from either early human
or maybe even early primate societies
where it's much more stable and you can
introspect that this feels much more
comforting being a part of a troop of a
100 humans where pretty much everyone is
pulling their weight and everyone
matters because they're doing their own
distinct thing. And that is a that's a
state that's a very stable state where
we're not infighting as much because
we're all sort of doing we all matter to
some degree. But when now there's uh
when there's infighting for you know
there's only there's five blacksmiths or
there's five podcasts or there's five
books about the evolution of the brain.
Now all of a sudden these other types of
things start emerging because we're no
longer all fulfilling a role that
matters. It feels like uh there's only
it feels like there's a ranking and only
one of these is going to matter. So I
think uh as an example of ways to reduce
this sort of status seeeking I see this
in sort of business all the time which
is the more you can create an
environment where it's not zero sum
where everyone's pulling their weight
and together we all win the more sort of
the best version of humans emerge the
the more zero sum it becomes and uh the
less divided the sort of roles and and
and what people are doing is the more of
these sort of I would argue sort of
primitive primate behaviors start
emerging
you know an early stage company so a
company of 30 people um has such
different dynamics than you know my last
company where you know when I was uh
when I left that we were 400 people the
social dynamics is so different and I do
think one could speculatively correlate
that to sort of our evolutionary history
here where in a 30 person company um you
don't need that much structure I mean if
you have if you have like people that
work well together that are aligned on a
mission that you know you get rid of
people that are in general mean-spirited
or have bad intent. You don't need a lot
of structure and process to get people
to work well together to support each
other to move in the common direction. I
think what that demonstrates when when
one observes that is that what's playing
out is an evolutionary program that got
groups of 30 humans to work really well
together. When you're at 400 people,
what very quickly happens and takes a
lot of work to fight this is you start
getting sort of internal factions emerge
because what splinters out is these
subgroups of you know 30 to 100 people
that then have their own points of view
and then it's very easy to us versus
them other groups and you start seeing
things break down and that's where you
know one mechanism for solving this is
very rigid hierarchies that's what the
military does um another mechanism is
embrace the chaos which is sort of a
little bit more what Google does another
mechanism is to have is to effectively
make it a satellite of different
startups which is what Amazon does where
each group is a kind of autonomous and
has very clean interfaces to other
groups so it can kind of so there's many
different sort of management approaches
to this but the breakdown I do think
emerges from humans did not evolve to
interact with you know 100,000 people um
we did evolve in an environment where we
interacted naturally with about a
hundred people and that's why that comes
very we don't need as much sort of uh
process to make that work but we do and
we scale it up.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's fascinating. I mean as
you say you could argue that Amazon has
one overarching goal to make money but
as soon as you increase the autonomy in
the organization it's a very human trait
isn't it? You were talking about the the
Machavevelian behaviors and the
deceptive behaviors and you just wonder
how much energy is just wasted with
infighting. And even I've made the
comment that in the military, you know,
they might be doing quite simplistic
jobs compared to Google, but even at
Google, there's an obsession with job
level.
>> That's the I mean, if you go off warer
or if you go on blind, that's the only
thing people talk about is their total
conversation and job level. So, you
know, I mean, maybe we should save the
the cynicism. But um so come coming back
to the um to the chapter. So we're
telling the story basically of of how
this metacognition and this predictive
apparatus um you know gave rise to an
entire suite of complex social behaviors
that that we see in primates which is
fascinating and maybe we should just
talk a little bit about um I call it why
bootstrapping. So it's like why why why
I think there was a um one guy at Toyota
Research was quite famous because he
would get people to ask why five times.
So you say why why why and it's almost
as if there's some magic number you know
like um everyone is only a certain
number of degrees of separation and it's
a similar thing that you only need to
ask why a few times and you'll always
get to some kind of base reason and
maybe that's why evolutionarily we have
you know two levels of of causation
metacognition in our brain you know we
we have the the arranular prefrontal
cortex and we have the granular
prefrontal cortex so I guess like one
potential question there is why is there
not a third level of asking why and what
would that look like and can you just
kind of sketch out that metacognition
picture in in general?
>> When we think about what uh when we
speculate what a granular prefrontal
cortex does um uh a reasonable framework
for it is it generates explanations of
an animal's behavior. It models an
animal's own behavior. So one uh sort of
cognitive tool to reason about that is
if it observes a rat wake up and have
certain hypothalmic activations and run
to in a certain direction to drink
water. Um it produces a representation
that could be interpreted as I uh am
explaining this behavior by I am hungry
as an animal. Um and so that can be
useful in a variety of ways. It can
trigger simulations to find alternative
solutions to satiate the same need.
Right? So if I if you think about this
if you put a rat in a novel situation
but the uh a granular prefrontal cortex
infers that right now I am hungry. Now
we can start triggering a bunch of
simulations to try and satiate the same
desire to fulfill this is a little bit
active inference land to fulfill sort of
what I believe uh about myself um
through alternative means um and enables
an animal to be flexible. Okay. So this
is sort of the the ex this is an
explanation of an animal itself. Why
would it be the case? So what I sort of
argue in the book is the granular
prefrontal cortex builds a model of that
model. Um so instead of a simulation
it's a simulation of the simulation. And
so what that would mean is if you if you
could as thought experiment if you could
ask uh let's let's go one step further
if or one step back. If we could ask the
basil ganglia, which you know is the
sort of reinforcement learning system,
why did you turn left to go uh in this
direction to drink water? It would just
say because that turning left maximizes
reward. The answer would always be the
same. If you ask the granular prefrontal
cortex, why did you turn left? You would
say, oh, because uh I'm thirsty. There's
a specific thing that me as an entity,
this animal I'm modeling wants to
achieve. But if you ask the granular
prefrontal cortex, you it would say,
well, I turned left because I am thirsty
and that made me think about ways to
satiate my thirst and I simulated going
to the left and I remembered water being
there because last time I was there
there was water and so I went to the
left. And so in other words, it enables
you to simulate different types of
simulations and reason about what you
would think in a new setting, which of
course enables you to think about what
someone else might be thinking. And we
do this all the time. I mean, someone
doesn't respond to a text message,
someone makes an odd facial expression
in a social interaction, and you know,
we're immediately trying to figure out
what is this person thinking, why would
they do this, etc. So, the the the
question first is why do we even need
this new level um at all? Um and sort of
I think one of the main adaptive values
is it enables uh u survival in the
politicking arms race because now if I
can simulate a simulation I can infer
why you might do a certain behavior how
to manipulate someone's knowledge um
your intentions behind things. So this
is why you would have one layer to go a
level above. I mean you could make an
argument that uh theoretically there
should be an infinite uh scaling up of
of y's. Um I think uh this is maybe a
copout but I think there is huge
energetic costs to any sort of scale up.
So what that means is the question is
not would there be benefits to a third
level of hierarchy but the question is
would the benefits of a third level of
hierarchy outweigh the massive energetic
costs of producing it. And so I think
that would be my first blush explanation
as to why we might only have two levels
instead of three or four because the
second level added a clear adaptive
value relative to the cost to survive in
the politicking arms race and the third
one perhaps was superfluous and
unnecessary relative to the energetic
cost. I I think um having that second
level of of metacognition, it it does a
lot of work, right? And I'm going to
talk a little bit about that now. But
one of the things is you can infer the
the intents and knowledge of others
through the same process of doing
simulations yourself. So you can kind of
imagine let's say yourself doing
something, but you can kind of swap out
the pointer to be someone else and swap
out the knowledge to be someone else.
And that's incredibly valuable. But the
knowledge thing is is really really
really interesting. So I I asked the
question last time and this is something
that I've been quite confused about and
I feel that reading this chapter has
actually really cleared it up for me um
which is about goals because when you
look one level down at the arranular
prefrontal cortex it's modeling intents
and then this granular prefrontal cortex
which is trying to seek explanations
about the level below which is the
arranular um prefrontal cortex um it
it's it's going a level of abstraction
up and it's modeling goals not not
intents but it's actually modeling
knowledge. It's what it's doing is it's
categorizing. So when you have a
simulation of simula
a simulation of simulations, what it's
doing is is it's creating a category. So
to the example you just gave before um
thirsty becomes a category. So rather
than it being a pointalistic intent, you
know, it's a little bit like saying I
can go and have a sandwich or I can go
and have McDonald's or my abstract
simulator could kind of draw a boundary
around those things and now I'm getting
food. So as well as being able to
categorize intents in yourself and other
people, you're also categorizing
knowledge and then it can be shared
mimemetically. So it's almost like just
going to that second level of
metacognition just just gives you so
much that you didn't have before.
100%. Yeah. I think um the uh
thinking about the level of granular
prefrontal cortex and the new primate
regions as enabling something akin to
knowledge I think is a really uh
wonderful way to look at it especi one
from the connectivity analysis and then
two just from what we mean by knowledge.
So connectivity analysis if you look at
superior temporal c uhuh superior
temporal sulcus and the temporal
parietal junction these are regions of
the posterior cortex that you know uh in
simple terms are at the very top of the
hierarchy. I mean they get multimodal
input from all the other regions of
sensory cortex. So a very sort of simple
um rule of thumb for understanding this
is just this models the rest of sensory
cortex. I understand the full rendering
of the simulation of the external world
that is happening. And this is where I
build a representation of that. And it
is perhaps no coincidence that's also
where we see um brain regions light up
when you're engaging in things like
theory of mind and solving false belief
tests. In other words, trying to infer
the knowledge of someone else. These
same regions light up. Um and so and
what do we mean by knowledge? Uh I would
argue that knowledge can mean a few
things. One is procedural knowledge
where um I just know how to do certain
motor behaviors. I don't think that's
what we mean. I think we mean more
semantic knowledge or episodic knowledge
which would be I know that water is over
there and I know that if I do this
behavior this will be the causal
outcome. That type of knowledge I think
is absolutely rendered in the mental
simulation. Um when I imagine certain
things h when I imagine the case of
lightning hitting the ground what do I
see afterwards? I see fire. and that
that that's the source of my knowledge
about the causal relationship between
these two things. So having a layer that
models the simulation enables me to
reason about my own knowledge and to see
what the effect of changing knowledge is
on behavior. And this of course enables
us to flexibly adapt to other people's
behavior and predict what they would do
under cases of different knowledge and
different intents.
>> Yeah, that's fascinating. But you did
say that the um there was a bit of a
riddle about the granular prefrontal
cortex because there was one study where
um it could be damaged and the person
would still score really highly in in
IQ. But you said it's about being able
to project yourself in simulations. You
know this kind of like abstract modeling
your own mind. So in this particular
case, how could the person still score
the same IQ without that part of the
brain? So this is such a cool story in
the history of neuroscience where um you
would think that if you look at a human
brain, I mean the granular prefrontal
cortex is this huge region in the front
of the brain. I mean it takes up a
gargantuan amount of space. You would
think that taking a chunk out of that
part of the brain would have a gross
effect on a human being. Um just like if
you took a part out of even a relatively
small region of the back of your brain,
which is where your visual cortex are,
you become hugely visually impaired. You
take a region of your motor cortex out
and humans become largely paralyzed for
months until they recover from that. You
take a region out of auditory cortex out
um and they can lose the ability to
recognize even words. So, so there's
relatively small regions of neoortex
that if there's damage to it, there's
gross obvious effects to the human
intelligence and behavior. And after
World War II, there were so many
patients with uh brain damage that you
know there's all these studies and
people could not figure out it was a
puzzle. What does this huge region of
prefrontal cortex do when people don't
have something seems off about them, but
it's not obvious what is wrong with
them? People would note personality
changes. They don't seem to be
themselves. But on sort of logic tests,
on IQ tests, it wasn't obvious they were
dramatically impaired. Um, in many
cases, and there was one famous case
where they could test someone before and
after because for uh surgical reasons,
they were going to remove parts of the
granal cortex. And this patient actually
improved in IQ tests. So render this
huge puzzle. What does this part of the
brain do? And so uh then if you track
sort of the studies from that point
forward, we start learning that what
granular prefrontal cortex does in large
part isn't related to these types of
logic puzzles. It's related to thinking
about thinking and modeling ourselves.
So for example um if you look at someone
who has damage to granular prefrontal
cortex um someone who has damage to the
hippocampus and then someone who has a
normal brain and you ask them something
very simple you give them a random word
and you say just tell me a story just
imagine a story of of you with this word
you could be the word could be
restaurant and you compare these stories
you immediately see something very
different. The people with hippocample
damage
give a very very rich story about
themselves but this the external world
misses details. So there's not a lot of
rich details about the external world.
This is consistent with the idea we
talked about with early mammals where
hippocampus helps render uh a simulated
external world. The people with granular
prefrontal damage could render a very
rich external world. They could tell you
the details of the leaves, the smell of
of food, uh exactly what a restaurant
looked like, but they themselves were
woefully missing from the stories. They
could not just they could not project
themsself into this imagined world. And
so then if we go back and look at all
these other things that that light up
granular prefrontal cortex, if you ask
someone to think about how they're
feeling, um granular prefrontal cortex
lights up, self-reference. But if you
ask another question such as what does
it look like outside the granular
prefrontal cortex does not activate.
APFC will activate in both cases. So we
start to see that it's in cases of
thinking about yourself and thinking
about others that this granular region
uh gets very activated. And now if you
go back and study these people more
deeply, you notice that they become
hugely impaired at false belief tests.
They can't recognize faux paw. So they
don't understand what's like not really
appropriate. um uh which of course makes
sense because how do I know what's
appropriate? I'm going to infer how you
feel about the things that I'm saying.
And so you see all of these sort of
mentalizing impairments that emerge, but
it's not related directly to these logic
puzzles that are typically in things
like IQ tests.
>> Yeah.
>> Um yeah, you mentioned the false belief
test. Can you just briefly sketch out
what that is?
>> Yes. So there's a there's a good picture
um if you want to hold it up or show on
the podcast. Okay. So, the way the test
works is you have Sally on the left who
has a basket and then you have Ann on
the right who has a box. So, Sally puts
a marble in the basket
um and then she walks away. Then Anne
goes over and moves the marble from
Sally's basket and puts it into her box
and then leaves. When Sally comes back,
where does she look for the marble? So,
it's so simple. But in order to figure
out that Sally will look into the box,
you have to understand that it's
possible for another mind to have
incorrect knowledge, to have false
belief about something. Um, and so young
children don't understand this. They
assume that knowledge is omnipotent.
Everyone has the same knowledge about
the world. But at a certain point, they
start learning that it's possible for
people to have false beliefs. And so we
actually know that um, uh, non-human
primates can do this. They've done
studies on macaks where you do exactly
the same salad test and you just look
where their eyes look when the person
comes back into the room to look between
the two boxes and they always look or
tend to look in the direction of where
that person thinks the marble is or the
piece of food is not where it actually
is. If you inhibit their granular
prefrontal cortex through an injection
or or another mechanism, this bias goes
away. They no longer look in the right
direction. There's lots of really good
evidence that this sort of false belief
mechanism is occurring in these primate
regions.
>> Yeah. And what really hit home to me is
that in a way it's not even knowledge.
It's all simulations. You know, it's
just simulations of of other agents. And
uh we we've always um kind of spoken
about knowledge in some weird plonistic
abstract sense. And I quite like the
idea that that the primitive form of
communication between humans is just
simulations even when we're speaking to
each other.
Yeah, exactly. So, how do we solve the
salan problem? It probably happens so
quickly, but we just simulate what would
we think if we were in Sally's shoes?
And then I realized, well, I would look
in in this place. And this helps us
reason about other people. And this begs
a really almost profound
uh question about, you know, how unique
is theory of mind? Uh this brings me to
a question that I've been asked multiple
times, which is does Chhat GBT have
theory of mind? if by theory of mind.
And so the evidence I I should stipulate
for anyone curious is if you ask GBT3
these sort of theory of mind puzzles, it
does terribly. So that's an easy one to
sort of discard out of hand. But if you
ask GBT4 these theory of mind puzzles,
it performs remarkably accurate like as
human level at these theory of mind
puzzles. And there's been people that
have explored is it just in the training
data? And there's good evidence that
it's not just because they're they're
you know they're just like regurgitating
what was in the training data. So does
this mean that Chad GBT has theory of
mind? So I think there's a few ways to
reason about this. One is what do we
mean by theory of mind? If by theory of
mind we just mean the ability to solve
these sort of false belief puzzles, then
I think you have to accept the fact that
yes, it can solve those tasks. Um
the problem is the way in which it
renders this model of other minds is not
through having a similar mind itself.
And so what this means is we should be
concerned doesn't mean it won't work
well but we should be concerned about
how well this will generalize to real
tasks where we might care about this
much more deeply. So for example with a
human because part of there's good
evidence to suggest that part of my
ability to reason about your mind is
because I have a mind that works quite
similarly. We are almost bound together
by some common mechanistic synergy
between the way in which our brains work
because our brains are quite similar
which which enables a lot of data
efficiency which is I'm pretty good at
predicting what people do not perfect
but pretty good at predicting what
people do because we're all people um
and there's similarities between how we
act and so that makes us quite data
efficient and decent at generalizing to
new situations where we put people in
new places that we've never seen before.
I can kind of guess well if I were in
that situation this is what I would do.
GBT4 has learned to build a theory of
mind simply by reading text of these
puzzles and so clearly it has some
mechanism to build a model of predicting
what people will do in certain
circumstances and differentiating
knowledge and intent etc. But the
concern is twofold. one, what will
happen if we take those types of models
and put them in very new situations that
are not based on just these puzzles, but
for example, we're asking them to
optimize a paperclip factory. You know,
that's a situation where we should be
concerned. How well will it do at
actually inferring what we mean by what
we say? Um, and the second is data
efficiency, which is how much data did
it have to see to build this model. If
it was a ton of data, then it's going to
be problematic. If we have these new
situations where we want to teach them
to model people's behaviors in this new
place, if it requires a ridiculous
amount of data, then it's always going
to sort of be slow to learn uh these
things and always be at risk of not
generalizing well when we put them in
these new situations. So um I my answer
here is nuanced which is I think if by
we theory of mind we mean solving puzzle
questions I think it's very hard to say
that that chatbt does not have some
model of human behavior but I do think
the human and primate mechanism for
doing so has a data efficiency uh gain
uh advantage and a mechanistic synergy
advantage in other words we can use
ourselves to reason about things um that
is relevant uh and if we want to have
these systems do a good job uh
listening to human requests. We should
be we shouldn't translate performance on
false belief tests to believing that
they'll do a good job correctly
inferring our intent and knowledge in
new situations.
>> Yeah, I I would agree with that. I think
chat GPT it's in the the world of text
and it's learned all of this structured
narratology and things on Reddit and
things on Twitter. And as we were saying
last week, you know, language has
evolved to be very simple. It has a it's
learnable by children. has a small
subspace. Um, but it is it is a real
kind of generalization over human
behaviors and it's and it's in this very
low resolution substrate. Whereas in the
Machavelian apes example that we were
talking about before, these are agents
performing real time sensing and
inferencing and making like you know in
the- moment judgments and they're
they're in this continuous sensor domain
where they have many many different
types of signals you know visual
signals, sound signals and also um you
know memory of of what happened in in
those dynamics just before. So um it
feels like a difference in kind to me
between those two situations. But it is
remarkable that in the the GPT domain
any kind of theory of mind could could
work.
One um good example of this I think is
is there a difference in our human
ability to predict behavior between a
car and a person. So the brain is always
able to model things it observes and
simulate it and predict what it will do.
So, I can look at a car and I can
imagine different colors of it and I can
imagine what will happen if I drop it
and it rolls down a hill and I can we
build models of things all the time. Um,
we build models of computers and models
of a you know, I'm just looking around
the room of books. So, the brain
produces models of things. Is the way
that the brain produces models of other
human behaviors exactly the same or is
there some unique advantage? And my my
argument is that there's something
unique happening when I'm building a
model of another person, which is I'm
leveraging my own inner simulation of
things as a as a useful prior to try and
predict what other people will do. And
so chatbt models human behaviors in a to
draw a crude analogy, the way we would
model a a random object, which is I'm
only modeling it based on seeing its
behaviors in certain situations with the
data I receive. On the other hand, when
we model someone else's behavior, we're
doing some form of projection and and
using the prior of how we would behave
and and we probably bootstrap part of
our model of human knowledge and intent
based on our own in introspection. And I
think in that way it is a difference in
kind.
>> Fascinating. I I completely agree with
that. The selfish gene is kind of saying
it doesn't matter what what you folks
do. Um the gene is kind of directing
your behavior and you don't really have
as much agency as as you think you do.
And it's a similar thing with language.
If you think of language as being a
super organism or a virus and we are the
hosts and information is being shared
mimemetically and and it's kind of you
know it's it's shaping our evolution but
it's also shaping our behavior. So it's
almost like when we become infected by
certain um memes it might be like
religion for example it completely um
you know it's almost like it
parasitically affects our behavior. But
I think there is a difference between
social memes and physical memes. So tool
use for example that doesn't seem to
have the same parasitic effect. So you
know the if you look at the behavioral
complexity of of apes because they don't
have these you know um novel virtual
memes um you know in in their in their
culture their behavior seems quite
monolithic compared to ours. But I just
wondered if you could kind of contrast
that next level of of mimisis.
So, um, there's been lots of great sort
of writing about the distinction in, you
know, the literature is typically called
cultural transmission between sort of
non-human primates and humans.
>> And, um, a lot of sort of the general
consensus here is that although there is
transmission amongst non-human primates,
which we see in particular with tool
use, um, it doesn't uh, sort of
accumulate in the same way that it does
with humans. In other words, um you
know, humans can pass a piece of
information to another generation which
that next generation will reliably copy
and then can merge with other new
information which they can then reliably
copy. And you do this over a thousand
years and you go from, you know, I know
how to use uh a whittle a bone into a
needle for sewing to all of a sudden now
I've built a loom, right? And these
ideas keep accumulating on top of each
other. Whereas in non-human primates,
you don't see the same type of
accumulation. And that's what I in like
a piffy way uh in the book call the
singularity that already happened, which
is once you enable these memes or ideas
to accumulate across generations, you
get what you're describing as this sort
of sort of mimetic uh organism that that
we are the substrate for. Um um for
sure. Now, what I think is interesting
here is one lens through which I like to
think about this is sources of learning.
So if you think about how non-human
primates learn, um there's sort of three
sources. One is they learn from direct
experience. So their own actual actions.
This is reinforcement learning writ
large. I do something, it succeeds, it
fails. Fine. Another is their own
imagined actions. This is the part that
evolved in early mammals. So I can
imagine doing five different strategies
to try and get to the sort of food over
there and I find the one that weren't
worked and that's a source of learning.
My model of the world became a source of
figuring out the right path. So my own
imagined actions what mentalizing
enabled with primates is this third
mechanism which is learning from other
people's actual actions. So, I can see
my, you know, if I'm a young
chimpanzeee, I can see my mother using a
stick to put into this termite mound and
pull it out and this complicated
behavior and eat food. And I don't have
to do my own behaviors to do that. I
don't even have to simulate doing it. By
watching her do that skill, I will adopt
and learn. But what non-human primates
don't have, which is what's very
uniquely human, is learning from other
people's imagined actions. This is sort
of the key breakthrough that happens
with language, which is the the
bandwidth through which non-human
primates can communicate what what we're
sort of calling knowledge here is only
through actions themselves. I can't
describe if I were a non-human primate
what I saw when I imagined five
different ways to try and hunt the boar
over there. I can just do it and you can
learn from what I what you saw me do.
But language enables us to share the
outcomes of our imaginations. And so
that is a way higher bandwidth mechanism
for translating information. So for
examp and and so that enables
accumulation across generations. So for
example, I mean it's so easy to think
about ways in which this would be
adaptive. Um you know two would be
sharing semantics. I go into the forest,
there's two snakes there. One bites me
and I'm fine. The other bites me and I
get really sick. I come back and I say
green snakes are okay. Red snakes don't
go near. And that semantic knowledge now
exists amongst the whole troop. In the
old world before there was language you
would have only the people surrounding
who saw this happen would have the
knowledge. Now I can translate it just
through I simulated in my mind the
episodic memory and I translate it to
everyone. The other is coordinated
planning. So before language it would
not be possible for you know five humans
to jump in trees and say okay here's how
we're going to hunt these boar. We're
going to stay silent and then I'm going
to whistle three times and then we're
all going to jump down and surround the
one in the back. That type of planning
is only possible because one person can
simulate something and then translate
and say hey when I imagine this happen
we succeed and other people of course
can edit that simulation say when I
imagine that happen I don't see us
succeed for this reason you can start
refining so the this ability to have a
source of learning from other people's
mental simulations
um is sort of what I would argue is the
source of this like very unique human
superpower that emerges from language
and of course now with such a high
bandwidth uh transference of mental
simulations, you do get this sort of
quas evolutionary process which is what
Richard Dawkins is talking about where
um you do have a process by which the
memes the ideas that do a good job
propagating are the ones that will
propagate and the ones that for whatever
reason reasons are not viral and either
don't do a good job of maintaining the
host so the ideas are bad and I end up
dying or that I just don't have an
incentive to share them they're not
viral those ideas die and so then you
get this sort of meme
evolution. Um, but to me the source is
the fact that language enables us to
share in our simulations becomes a much
higher bandwidth communication
mechanism.
>> I'm fascinated by this idea of the the
meme itself being an agent, being a
virtual agent and it in in expressing
its agency, it needs to manipulate us.
So you might argue as you do in your
book that there has to be some kind of
traceable chain down to the basil
ganglia. So we have many many levels of
bootstrapping and at some point the
thing exists because the basil ganglia
says oh that's good I like that. So then
we have one level and then we have
another level and then we have like the
the mimosphere and it's almost as if
that thing is manipulating us because
when you have weekly emergent
macroscopic phenomena um part of the
definition of of emergence is surprise.
So it's macroscopically surprising. So
it does something which is completely
unexpected and unlike the thing that
went below. And it's just kind of weird
that it might be manipulating us down
here, but doing something completely
different up there.
>> Yeah. So, I think there's probably
uh this is mostly fun speculation, but I
think there's probably two ways if we're
if I'm going to draw analogies to brain
regions and intellectual features of the
human brain. I think there's probably
two lightweight ways we could think
about why memes become sort of
attractive. uh one would be um sort of
the older vertebrae like structures. So
this would be uh basil ganglia plus
amydala. Um and these are things a meme
that makes me feel fear um or makes me
uh think that unless I take an action
something bad is going to happen to me
and one of those actions has to be
sharing it then then that's going to be
highly viral. um you know if you make me
afraid for my family's well-being you're
going to activate my my amygdala and
even if there's only a 2% chance that
this is true I might still share it
right so you get these sort of we're not
good humans are not good at dealing with
low probability high magnitude events
which is another brain constraint the
other key thing that also exists at the
level of sort of vertebrae uh early
vertebrae like structures is a
preference for surprise um so in order
for reinforcement learning to work well
um it's very effective and we see this
in AI systems um to make people pursue
actions that are novel because that's
one way in which we can uh explore new
areas and learn new actions that um and
sort of explore the space of possible uh
choices to make. This is one intrinsic
way to get trial and error to work. So
the way you know casinos make money from
you is they hack into this sort of
preference for surprise. So they have
something you know if there's a 0%
chance of winning you would never play.
Um but if there's a 48 a net 48% chance
um meaning in the long run you'll lose
money but every once in a while there's
some surprising thing um that actually
is over the threshold of being worth it
to the basil ganglia because the
surprise is so exciting is one way to
think about it. So I think you get
something that creates sort of innate
fear um or uh some great outcome or
surprise you get these older structures.
I think with mamalian structures, I
think there is sort of a um active
inference play here and you could even
correlate it to granular prefrontal
cortex with things like identity where
um if you give me some information that
uh is consistent with the my model of
myself and I'm highly motivated to
maintain my model of myself for a
variety of reasons that you know we can
talk about. um then I'm more likely to
maintain this belief versus if you give
me information that's inconsistent with
my model of who I am um people are
highly likely to reject these beliefs.
So, so this is another speculative way
to think about um why memes sort of
persist within their little echo
chambers and it can quickly become sort
of identity wars is if my if one's
identity is consistent with a certain
set of beliefs then that almost creates
a gated wall for certain types of memes
to enter. it becomes much harder for
certain ideas to be entered into my mind
and it creates a very porous film for
other types of ideas that are consistent
with my identity become very easy for me
um to adopt and I think that's another
uh if we're going to frame memes as
having agency one strategy by which a
meme would seek to survive is you find a
way to be consistent with certain
people's view of themselves and the
world so that what you're doing is
you're reinforcing it as opposed to
challenging it. Now there is a very
clear difference though which is the
human brain is analog and these machine
brains are digital and there's pros and
cons of each of these. So a digital
brain Jeff Hinton talks about this to
make sure I'm citing these cool ideas.
Um but he has a great talk where he very
well describes that the benefit of a
digital brain is it's immortal where um
all the weights are stored in sort of
binary so I can very easily transfer it
to different brains but it's hugely
energy inefficient.
um because uh I need to model everything
exactly to be copyable. But the human
brain is way more efficient and it but
it's not copyable because the
information exists in the physical
representation of the analog connection
between all these neurons, the actual
rep the actual protein receptors that
exist in them, the gene expressions, all
this crazy stuff that makes it
non-copyable. And so um
it'll be interesting to see um what is
the energy efficiency for example of an
AI digital AI system that actually does
attempts to recapitulate a human brain
that might be very uh energy uh
inefficient. Um and it might open the
door for a whole new area of research I
think would be really fascinating which
is building analog brains. um can we
have these systems that actually work in
a more analog way and the way they pass
information to each other this is also a
Jeffrey Hinton idea is by teaching each
other um and because they are AI systems
uh they can teach each other with better
fidelity than a human uh because they
can actually share probabilistic
outcomes opposed to just the words we
say and they can generate way more
samples for each other than a human
could because they can live much longer
etc. But there's a whole emerging world
of, you know, the distinction between
these digital machines that are immortal
but very energy inefficient and then
analog machines that are much more
energy efficient but less good at
translating information. Um, and I to
one of your points that I think is
really key is one of the main things
missing that I don't think is talked
about enough and maybe there'll be a
breakthrough soon that would be great
but I I don't see very clear ideas
uh over the horizon that will solve this
is the continual learning problem. I
would say this is one of the essential
lines that differs uh that
differentiates biological brains from
modern AI systems which is um the way in
which AI systems are trained are such
that we cannot let them continuously
learn from new experiences because it
disrupts the old information they have.
So whether that is an architectural
constraint or something that needs to
change in the underlying learning
algorithm itself lots of open research
and debate about that. But the fact
remains that if you allowed chat GBT to
learn from every chat that happens to
it, it would get rapidly dumber.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and that is not the case with humans.
We can continuously update our
information. Our representations are
robust. And I think for many of the
applications for AI systems that are
going to be most impactful. Continual
learning is going to be an essential
component because we're going to want to
bring an AI agent in, show it new
information, and immediately have it
incorporate that without forgetting old
things. So I think that is very clearly
a line that um there's a lot of really
interesting research happening and a lot
of research left to be done.
>> Why are we superior to animals?
>> So there's been such a long history of
us pontificating on the various chasms
or attempting to create a chasm
intellectually between us and other
animals. Um the most famous form of this
which I think still shows threads in in
modernity is from Aristotle where uh he
sort of took the same kind of ideas that
you see in McLean's triune brain where
you know other animals might have these
basic instincts they might have some
form of emotions but what they all lack
which which humans uniquely have is this
notion of reason. We can uniquely reason
about things in the world. And I think
as I try to argue in the book and I
think most comparative psychology
demonstrates quite clearly is there's
clearly forms of reasoning that we see
in other animals. Um and so uh you know
of all of the different abilities and
capacities that seem unique to humans,
the one that stands out as most salient
is undeniably language. um because uh we
we despite many painstaking attempts
have not even been able to teach
chimpanzees, bonobos or gorillas uh to
speak with with the same degree of
fidelity of of humanlike language. Um
now there is some controversy as to the
extent to which uh did Kanzi and Koko uh
and Wu pass the threshold that we define
as language and so that can be debated
where do we draw the line? Um but
undeniably most people would agree that
these uh you know non-human primates do
not learn language naturally without
painstaking attempts to teach them and
and when they do learn language it does
not show the same sort of flexibility as
humans. Now what makes language unique
um is two things. One is declarative
labeling. So there is a distinction
between imperative labels and
declarative labels. An imperative label
is is learning that a phrase, a Q, uh
leads, if you take an action in response
to a Q, you get a reward. So, when a dog
uh responds to a specific Q with a
response and then you give them a treat,
that's not what we define as language.
It's an imperative label. A declarative
label is when I say dog and in your
head, you know, that references a
concept or a thing. Now, we have a label
for a concept or a thing. And so, uh,
it's not at all clear that other
species, uh, perform these types of
declarative labeling. And if they do,
um, it surely independently evolved.
Like, we're we're quite confident that
early primates didn't have this, um,
ability. Um, the second thing that makes
language unique is grammar. Um, so we
can take these declarative labels that
reference things or actions and then we
can weave them together in certain
structure and the structure itself has
meaning. [snorts] So that basic example
is just the ordering of phrases. So if I
say Ben hugged James, that means
something different than James hugged
Ben. Despite the fact that it's the same
phrases um or the same declarative
labels, the order uh presents meaning.
Um so there's a whole interesting world
of of why language, if it is the case
that language is the fundamental
difference, why why is it language that
has allowed humans to sort of take over
the world? And that's another
interesting topic we should discuss. Um
but I would argue that primarily what
makes humans different is language. Um
and and Aristotle's idea of reason uh we
see at least in smaller forms and other
animals.
>> Yeah. I mean it's quite interesting
because because you said right at the
very beginning that you know yeah
Aristotle um he spoke about the rational
soul that we have and even in the 20th
century you know we spoke about things
like mental time travel and our sense of
self and tool use and it's really
interesting because we look in the
animal kingdom and one by one all of
these things that we thought placed a
bright line between us and animals faded
away. Some people think that language is
a continuum that there's just a
gradation that you know if you scale up
the um the brain of of the ape that you
will get human language. Is that the
case?
>> So I'm uh the reason I I'm very
skeptical of that claim is we don't see
variance in language abilities based on
brain size. Children who learn language
at the age of four um still have
small brains relative. I mean, I I
actually I'm not sure the exact brain
size comparison, but I'd be curious the
brain size of a four-year-old child
relative to an adult chimpanzeee. Um,
just based on uh, you know, volume. Um,
the other the the other interesting case
is Yeah. Hom flores floresensis. Yeah.
Homophoresens.
>> Oh yeah. From Indonesia. The ones with
the small brain.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yes. So, homophoresens is a great case
study here because um they uh we found
fossils of uh ancestral humans on
Indonesia who were effectively miniature
humans. I mean they had shrunk in size
to I think they were like 3 and 1/2 ft
to four feet tall. Um and their brain
capacity we can look at their fossilized
brains had shrunk actually from our
ancestral human. So they were um
marginally larger than the size of a
modern chimpanzeee brain. Um and yet
they showed a lot of signs of superior
human intelligence despite having
smaller brains. They showed tool use
that was akin to ancestral humans. They
had um uh Aldwin tools which is
supposedly a sign of of uh uniquely
human intelligent tool making. And so
that is suggestive of the idea that
whatever uh unique intellectual
capacities humans earned around 2
million to 1 million years ago was
present despite their shrinking brain.
So either one has to argue that language
evolved much earlier which some people
do or whatever sort of proto language
emerged back then was present even when
these brains started shrinking which
suggests to me which is actually uh
aligned with the the ideas in the
language game and my understanding of
them which is a great book um is that
fundamentally what's unique is we have
an instinct to learn language it's not
that we have some unique capacity for
language and I think that is a a key
difference um that uh we can talk about
because when you look at children who
learn language there are two very unique
features of of how they go through
language learning um by the young age of
around two um uh they're already uh
engaging in uh protocon conversations.
So they they you actually a younger
infant will will pause will match the
pausing of their of their mother. So
even if they're just babbling, they will
engage in the synchrony of babbling time
intervals. And so uh that is clearly a
demonstration of some initial instinct
which which demonstrates the ability for
me to want to engage in some turntaking
action with you.
>> The other unique thing that emerges a
little bit later is joint attention. um
and where uh human children will uh
uniquely attempt to get their parents to
engage in attention towards the same
object. Um and scientists have gone to
painstaking efforts to demonstrate that
this attempt to get a parent to engage
in attention of an object is not the
attempt to get the object. So a child or
an infant will be dissatisfied if the
parent doesn't look at the object, but
they get the object. So a third party
comes in and hands it to them. they're
dissatisfied. If the parent looks at
them and is excited when they're
pointing at an object, the kid will also
not be satisfied. But only when the
parent looks at the object and then
looks back at the kid and smiles is the
child satisfied. So there's this
instinct to uh to engage in conversation
and to jointly attend to things. Um
which gives us the sort of instinctual
foundation on which you can start adding
declarative labels. Because when you
have joint attention to something and
you're paying attention to this turn
taking, it enables you to to label
things and say, "Well, this means run or
this means book." Um, so so I think um I
think it make that all of that makes it
hard to argue that it's just a
consequence of a scaled up brain. Um,
one of the things that that's really
fascinating is that animal communication
seems extremely superficial. And when I
say superficial, I mean that when you
take different populations of the same
species or different species, the the
kind of the expression, the complexity,
it's it's very very simple. We don't see
this like incredible fractionation and
divergence that that we see in in human
language. And as you articulated just a
minute ago, a big part of that is this
declarative labeling, which is that, you
know, one of one of the reasons
presumably for language is the ability
to um do variable binding on symbols. So
to say, you know, this thing is a dog,
that thing's a bear, and to be able to
dynamically um manipulate that. It seems
to me that you can think of language as
a form of agentic communication. So the
difference between humans as as
languages is that we are agents and
agents is about being able to kind of
like, you know, have your own
directedness and plan many steps ahead
and take control of your environment and
so on. So the difference in
communication with animals is the
information content is more in the
environment around them. Whereas for you
know human languaging a lot of it comes
from the agent itself. So I just
wondered whether you could think of any
weird way to distinguish human
languaging from animal communication.
One line that I think uh there's some
good evidence uh to suggest exists
between human communication and
non-human primate communication is
humans have much more of a desire to
share
>> uh what's going on in our own mind. Um
there is a a unique pleasure we have
from sharing our thoughts. And uh and
when we look at the communication styles
that happens in non-human primates,
there's much less of a desire even for
these uh uh when we go through these
language learning experiments where they
have forms of communication. There's
much less of a desire to share thoughts
that are going on in uh in one's mind.
And one one line there's some
controversy around this is humans from a
very young age will ask questions.
They'll inquire as to what's going on in
someone else's head. And uh with the
exception of maybe Kanzy who there was
some argument maybe asked questions, you
did not see non-human primates probe the
mind of other individuals even though we
know they have theory of mind. We know
when they're trying to uh deceive others
or they're trying to learn actions by
obser observation um they clearly engage
in theory of mind but when it comes to
language they weren't interested in
inquiring as to what someone is thinking
about. And so I think in that sense
there's uh an agency to uh language
being a tool for inquiring as to what's
going on in someone else's mind and
sharing what's going on in your mind.
And this is where I think language is in
part part of why language is a
superpower because it provides a
completely unique source of learning and
data um or data for learning. So so
non-human primates can engage in
learning through observation because I
can see someone take actions as you said
with imitation learning. I can see you
open a puzzle box to get food and I can
learn from observing your actual
actions. And so uh and the way I do that
is because I can infer the intent of
what you're trying to do and then I can
figure out which of the actions are
relevant and which are irrelevant. So a
monkey um and a chimpan or a or an ape
will ignore irrelevant actions when they
observe you uh do a task. So uh they've
done these experiments with humans and
chimpanzees where they do all these
actions to open a puzzle box and they do
some random actions and uh you know
chimpanzees will ignore the random
actions which suggests they can infer
the intent of it. Um which is great but
chimpanzees don't learn from what's
going on in your head. Um, and so the
ability to learn from from other mental
simulations is what's so powerful about
language because I can say, you know,
and uh I just went over to that forest
over there and I saw a red and blue
snake and I I saw that the red snake is
really dangerous, but the blue snake is
not uh because the blue snakes bit me
and nothing happened. Um, and so I share
that that episodic memory and now
everyone has that knowledge even though
that was just in my mental simulation.
or when planning a hunt, you know, a
group of five humans, I can imagine a
strategy of how all five of us are going
to coordinate, see it succeed in my
mind, and then share the results and the
plan with everyone. So, language enables
us to tether our mental simulations to
each other. Um, and I think there there
is a sense of uh agency in the idea that
there's a purpose uh to that. There's a
there's a valitional purpose to the
communication. um the neurological
underpinnings of uh communication that
occurs in non-human primates is more
analogous to our emotional expressions
than it is to language. And we see this
uh uh also in the brain. So like uh you
know monkeys and and non-human apes have
these innate expressions that they do
which are this genetically hard-coded
and we know that because it's the same
in uh even across species often who have
never interacted with each other. Um,
and it comes from neurological
structures similar to our laughing and
crying.
>> Um, and so this and so it's it's clearly
a hard-coded emotional expression. And
in that sense, it doesn't have the same
valition because I'm not doing this
action to communicate a concept to you.
I'm doing this action as an innate
response to a cue or a feeling I have.
Um, so yeah, I think there there's
there's meat to that idea.
>> Well, um, a few few things to explore
there. I mean first of all we should
just talk about how we became a
collective intelligence after the fact.
So I'm not sure whether that's unique to
humans if you look at other forms of of
collective intelligence. There's always
a kind of juosition between the
intelligence of the individual versus
the collective. And actually usually you
find that having very intelligent
individuals um is not good for the
intelligence of the collective. But
what's interesting about humans is like
we clearly didn't evolve as a collective
intelligence. So we had this kind of
bootstrapping process where we were very
very useful you know independent agents
and then this collective intelligence um
just emerged out out of nowhere. So is
that is that an interesting observation?
There's different degrees of
collectiveness um and and so I think we
can uh draw distinctions between um
different flavors of collectiveness but
I don't think humans are uniquely
collective. So for example, the
imitation learning of non-human primates
is a form of collective intelligence
because you can teach one member of a
chimpanzeee troop how to use a tool and
then over time the rest of the troop
will learn just through observation. So
that's a sense of collective
intelligence. Many vertebbrates and and
likely the first vertebrae uh you can
even see fish will learn through
observation. Um in other words when a
fish uh uh swims in one a certain
direction to get food other fish can see
that fish do that and follow them. there
can be an instinct to follow other uh um
others around you. Um so we so I think
there there is flavors of collectiveness
um that exists um uh across many
different species. But what's unique
about the collectiveness in humans is
the fidelity with which we transfer our
mental simulations enables it to
accumulate across generations. And in
that sense, it has its almost its own,
you know, you could argue it becomes, it
has its own agency or is its own thing.
Um, because it can actually go through
its own process of evolution as ideas
propagate through generations of people.
Um, which is not the same thing that you
see in other animals.
>> Yeah. I mean, a couple of things on
that. I mean, first of all, I would
quite like to distinguish
knowledge and intelligence. So,
collective intelligence and intelligence
in general is is a process of
discovering models. And when I just to
sort of get the language down here um I
will use models and skills and knowledge
um pretty much interchangeably. So I I
think of like an intelligent process as
epistemic foraging. So just finding
interesting models and then they can be
discovered and and shared by by other
people. So um it's a little bit like
when you distribute a GPU workload um
you can do like model parallelism and
you can do data parallelism. So you can
either split up the the the the CPU like
you know the processing or you can split
up the actual um representation. So I
think the kind of collective
intelligence that you've just been
speaking about is okay we've got all of
these independent agents and they are
finding models and sharing models and
you know the models get refined over
time and and and it adapts and so on.
But I also [snorts] think a big
important element is sharing the the
computation. So even though there's
there's there's some uh kind of
redundant work going on but you know um
epistemic areas over here are being
explored but also in many cases the same
problems are being explored but in
slightly different variation. So we're
kind of sharing the workload with other
humans.
>> Yes, I think that totally makes sense.
the there's some interesting ideas in AI
here actually where there's this concept
of knowledge distillation
um in AI where uh one way in which you
can have model A teach model B the
things that model A knows
um one way is you can wholesale copy the
parameters of model A um of course
that's totally biologically implausible
there are aspects of of parameter
copying which is the components of our
brain that are genetically hard-coded
that is a version of parameter copying
um but but for for other uh applications
it's not it's not feasible to just copy
parameters or it's maybe not desirable.
So knowledge distillation is saying okay
well we can have a set of data um that
we uh give model A and we either look at
the outputs of model A or the layer
before the outputs so we can see sort of
more richness in its representation of
of the input you give it and then take
those that data that almost labeled data
to model B and then train model B on it.
So that's uh distilling some of the
knowledge through almost training model
B to try and act similarly to model A.
And so that type of uh information
transfer um I think does occur in uh
non-human primates and that's imitation
learning. However, um it is not nearly
as uh rich because what happens in
non-human primates is it's primarily
grounded in just the actions that I'm
taking. um which is much less rich than
I can share not only the the data of
what you see me actually do but I can
also include in the data I'm
transferring to you um things that
happen only in my mind um and that that
opens the door for much more
transference of of and the word you use
the computations that I'm performing
yeah
>> um so I think it's absolutely absolutely
true
>> before we were um learning in the
physical world so we were learning from
physical things that we were directly
observing and now we are learning from
imagined actions, but there's a bit of a
latent component to language as well.
So, for example, um someone might come
up to me and say, "Oh, the blue swirly
thing is over there." And I'll say,
"Well, I don't know what you mean about
the blue swirly thing because I've I've
never seen one before." So, there's this
kind of um uh inference process. And
this is where it starts to get really
interesting because there's a diffusion,
right? There's a kind of um there's a
message passing that happens between all
of the different agents and it's filling
in missing information. So even though
many of the agents wouldn't have seen
anything like what we're talking about,
sometimes it can be filled in with
subsequent um interactions with people
and sometimes it can just become a kind
of latent category which can be filled
in later. So there's this real diffusion
process going on which I think is quite
difficult to articulate. Part of what's
so interesting about language uh is it's
still an area of such controversy
amongst cognitive psychologists,
linguists and even AI people. Um and so
much is still you know unsettled about
it. Um there are still you know debates
today. I mean there's debates today
about whether language is primarily a
tool for thinking or communication. Um
and uh and most people were you know
Chsky is the most famous proponent of
the idea of language for thinking. So uh
you know and he has evolutionary
arguments that language initially
evolved not as a tool for communication
but for our own process of thinking and
then later was accepted or or used for
communication. Um that's a minority
view. Um and then other people argue
which I I'm more amendable to that
language was primarily used as a tool
for communicating. Um and these ideas
actually are reemerging with language
models because uh the way language
models learn about the world in some
sense is uh language becomes the
reasoning tool itself which is more
Chsky like even though you know there's
a lot of um you know I think the the
success of language models I think in a
lot of ways discredits a lot of Chsky's
ideas and we can talk about that but but
interestingly the fact that we're using
language as the fundamental mechanism
for reasoning and thinking is actually
somewhat chosky like um versus language
is communication. The idea is language
is a a condensed set of tokens that I'm
passing between minds but the goal the
real communication I'm trying to share
with you is what's going on in my mind.
In other words, the mental simulation,
the more mamlian component here, um, uh,
the rendered 3D world is what I'm trying
to transfer to you. And I condense it
into this code that then you, you know,
reverse engineer back into a mental
simulation. And uh theory of mind, one
reason why language might might be so
rare in the animal kingdom is
mentalizing theory of mind, which is
relatively rare in the animal kingdom,
is a prerequisite because in order for
me to reverse engineer the language code
you've provided me, I need to be able to
infer what you might have meant by what
you're saying and reason about why you
would have said this and what knowledge
you have and and etc, etc. Um so so yes
so I think language is is intended to
cue to another person um uh to render
something in their mind. This is also
where you know teaching is so important
is is such a key aspect of language
learning because uh we can infer you
know what declarative labels is this
person aware of and when they're
confused then you can start you have to
start trying to iterate to understand
what are they confused about uh that I'm
saying that I can disambiguate for them.
So, there's also a disambiguation
process where you ask follow-up
questions when you feel like you don't
fully understand uh what's going on in
someone else's head.
>> Yeah. I mean, the the guardrails thing
is interesting because they they they're
not necessarily thinking guardrails,
they're also pragmatic guardrails. And
there's a really interesting um figure
in in in the book actually. Yeah, here
it is. And it talks about how language
is is um sharing information over
generations. So without language, you
know, we learn a little bit inside a
generation, then it goes to, you know,
pretty much back to zero again. But now
we have the ability to to pass on these
mometic bits of information over several
um generations. But the thing is there's
a real structure to it. I think of it as
a bit like, you know, um a directed as
cyclic graph. So it's a tree structure
and every single bit of knowledge that
we discover kind of stands on the
shoulders of giants. So it needs all of
the things that we discovered
beforehand. So in a sense, you know,
we're all of these little agents and
we're doing this epistemic foraging. So,
you know, we're finding new skill
programs, we're sharing them and so on.
But it's almost like we shouldn't think
of the mass as being like an entire
convex hole. It's only on the boundary
where all of the creativity and and all
of the information sharing happens, you
know, like on the surface of this object
that that's being created. And what I
mean by that is like now in modern
cities, for example, you can't live
without a driver's license. You can't
live without the internet. you need to
do things a certain way and even though
it's not technically constraining our
brains and how we think like we live in
a very very constrained and weird world
now. Yeah, great totally great point.
There's um we are there's a biological
constraint as to how much knowledge a
given human brain can contain. And so
one lens through which to see the last
you know 100,000 years especially the
last you know hundred years is us
finding solutions to getting past the
biological constraint of human brains.
Language was one tool because it used to
be the case that uh all of the
information that a given entity learned
needed to be learned by my brain um
within my lifetime. And language enables
us to our group to have shared
knowledge, but not every brain contains
all of the knowledge. So if you think
about a troop of 100 100 people, it's
possible for that hundred people and all
their descendants for a thousand years
to have tons of skills despite the fact
that any one brain never had all of the
skills. So someone becomes really good
at, you know, uh hunting, someone
becomes really good at weaving uh animal
skins into clothing and all of these
types of skills. And actually there are
cases um in anthropology of groups of
humans that get separated from each
other of uh their technology degrading
because there is a limit uh there is a a
minimum number of brains needed to
contain uh and store a certain amount of
information in the absence of writing.
And so writing language was maybe
innovation one here. Writing was another
innovation which is great. Now we can
more reliably transfer these ideas
across generations even if there are
gaps. In other words, even if there's a
period of time for maybe two
generations, no brains contain it. A
third generation can go back to the
writing and pick up that knowledge. Um,
and then of course now with uh, you
know, with the internet, we have just
scaled up writing even more. Um, but
you're absolutely right. Uh, you know,
sometimes I think about this as like,
you know, if me and a group of 20
friends ended up on an island, um, how
much of, uh, of human and we were the
only 20 humans left. Not that I think
about this all the time. Uh but it is it
is crazy how little of human knowledge
would be contained in our 20 brains. How
how dramatically we would degrade
essentially like we've got this thing
where we've got all of these different
brains and individual people can um you
know have about 150 friends or
something. You know it's it's the the
social dumbar limit. But as you say,
because we have like this ability to to
share simulations and we have common
myths and so on, we can actually address
a much larger carrying capacity of of
people and and knowledge and um actually
you said something really interesting in
the book which is four things, right? So
bigger brains, specialization, more
brains, bigger population size and
writing and sharing simulations and the
internet and all of these things. So so
we've increased our carrying capacity
and like now something very interesting
and arbitrary has emerged. So, we've got
all of these different specializations
of skills and I guess the question is
where does it end? Has it converged?
Like could could we could we carry much
more knowledge than we already have or
would we have to wait for a top down
kind of genetic pressure for our brains
to get a bit bigger? Again,
I mean I think we are um we are about to
go through this. the Google and the
internet has become has turned us all
into epistemic hybrids. I mean our
Google has become a shared knowledge
store um that we all use and of course
there's problems because now there's sub
areas on the internet where we can use
different knowledge stores and now we
live in you know uh these different
epistemic bubbles and that creates
political problems as well. um uh but we
have already become hybrids where we use
technology uh to be to to overcome
limitations in our own brains. Writing
is a tool to overcome challenges in
memory um and uh at times thinking. Um
the internet uh has become uh you know a
tool to answer any question at a whim
and and some people have concerns with
this because it can also uh atrophy
parts of our brain that maybe we want.
Um so for example um through mere
introspection I will say once I started
using Google maps as a kid um my the
part of my brain that was learning how
to navigate a city through you know
actually remembering the grid and map of
a city just started atrophying like now
I have no capacity to do that whereas my
dad you know you take him to any new
city and he's like you can see him
rendering a map of the city in his mind
and he won't use Google maps. Um, now
now one could argue that it doesn't
matter because I'll always have Google
Maps, so why do I need this skill? Um,
and then another argument would be um
that atrophying may have other
consequences in my life and it would be
important for me to go through the
cognitive exercise even though
technology enables me to do it. And and
we do make these trade-offs at different
times. Why do we teach kids arithmetic?
They can always just use a calculator.
But we deem it important for us to go
through the process of understanding
arithmetic even though technology can
already do a better job for us. And so
this new frontier with you know using
large language models and there's some
really cool things with education
happening like uh you know in Khan
Academy they're working on building
language models to help children go
through reasoning steps which is a
really cool application because instead
of just asking the question it'll probe
the student to go through a process so
they can come to the conclusion
themselves. And so so uh there's a
there's a um uh sort of uh pessimistic
and optimistic world here. an optimistic
world is these new AI systems um are
actually going to be a new step forward
in uh sort of uh cyborgizing ourselves
but it's not necessarily going to be as
um atrophying as something like Google
because these systems won't only just
get us sort of the dopamine hit of a
factual answer but will also guide us
towards better understanding how it came
to this conclusion to ensure that we
understand uh when we're probing and
asking questions that's an optimistic
state of the world The pessimistic state
of the world would be that we offload
more and more of our own sort of
cognitive reasoning to these systems and
we become even more atrophied uh in
these abilities and and that might be
you know not a good world we want to
live in if uh we keep offloading more
and more of reasoning to systems that um
and we lose the ability to do it well
ourselves.
>> Yeah. So I've been thinking about this a
lot recently. So um I mean I was
involved in a startup that did
transcription and language models and
augmented reality glasses. So the idea
was you know you can be in a lecture and
by the way I still think this is very
useful for people with um you know
accessibility concerns like heart of
hearing or something like that but you
know um but you know we were kind of
thinking of it as something which can
augment your cognition. So you're in a
lecture and now you don't need to pay
attention to the lecturer because you
know you're transcribing and GPT is
making notes for you and so on. And I
think this is really wrong. But you give
a counter example of satnav. So we don't
need to read the maps anymore. Uh
because we can now externalize that
cognition. Um but I feel like this is
different. So you're in a you're in a
lecture or something like that. And now
all of these kind of AI language tools,
they are a form of understanding
procrastination, right? So understanding
or intelligence is is the process of
creating a model. So you're creating a
simulation and in order to create a
simulation you actually have to think
and you you know you normally think you
externalize the thinking a bit you do
some writing and you pay attention. Now,
here's the thing. In the situation,
there are so many more cues, right?
Because it's in 4D. You can hear things.
You can see things. It's a social
activity. It's a physical activity. Even
the the sort of the the dance, the the
performativity of the of the lecturer,
it's all information. It helps you
understand. So, now I'm transcribing the
thing. And people say, "Oh, it's okay. I
I can just read the transcription later
and I can understand it." Well, yeah,
maybe. But you're already at a
disadvantage. And you probably won't
because this procrastination, you're
just like you're paying it down the
line. You're saying, "I might do it
later. I might do it later and you never
will. Then that's going to create a
society of automatons that just don't
think for themselves.
>> Yeah. Well, I think that's a very uh I'm
sort of torn between the optimistic and
pessimistic uh state uh of the future,
but I think there's a very good argument
behind what you're saying. So, I'm not I
don't uh I definitely don't reject that
out of hand. Um, I think the I actually
really liked the um, uh, analogy to sort
of model based verse model free that you
were suggesting there because that is
actually applies very well towards
Google Maps because when my dad
navigates a city, he has a model of the
world and he's engaging in this model
based planning of how to get somewhere.
When I use Google Maps, I've
externalized the model and all I do is
respond to the cue of when do I turn
right or left. And so and so I think
that is absolutely a a good way to to
think about this which is we use
technology to externalize building
models which can sometimes make things
more efficient because then we can just
be model free actors. Um but there are p
places like in the example you're
suggesting where we really want people
to engage in the more painful hard
process of building models of things. Um
and in those cases uh you know obviously
it's dangerous to make it so easy to
externalize these models.
>> Yeah. I mean it's it's hard to
articulate. I think part of it is um
it's a kind of acquiescence. So I think
you're sequestering your agency when you
externalize too much of your cognition
particularly if it's parts of your
cognition that are useful in the sense
that it has core knowledge which will
generalize and help you acquire new
knowledge or um it's just the the the
protoability of you know um discovering
knowledge. It's just your intelligence
and you're not exercising that muscle.
So you become acquiescent and then you
become less of of an agent. And from a
collective intelligence point of view, I
think this, you know, we're just saying
like language and intelligence is about
discovering knowledge. And if we are all
sequestering our agency and becoming
less intelligent as individuals, as a
collective, maybe we will suffer. But
it's one of those things that it's so
easy for us now just to make grand
statements about this. And people in 200
years will look back on this and just
laugh and say, oh, you know, it's a
little bit like when when they
introduced bicycles. Um they were
saying, "Oh, bicycles are there's a
moral panic apparently because they
said, "Oh, women will start cheating on
their husbands and using the bicycles to
go to the next town." [laughter]
>> You know,
>> that is an interesting fact.
>> Yeah. Well, I think um I I I think
history is such a good I love thinking
about history as a tool when trying to
reason about how people in the future
will think about us because I think, you
know, we are the people in the future to
the past, which is obvious, but um a
useful tool. So for example, in some
sense we already live in this dystopian
world when it comes to physical
exercise. I mean roll back the clock 500
years and most people most people uh
didn't have to think about physical
exercise as much because most work
required physical exercise. So we
exercise with our work and so much of
jobs uh at least in the developed world
are information related jobs where we
don't exercise and so we go to the gym.
I mean, the gym is a is a weird if the
like if aliens came down and observed
gyms, it would be an anthropologically
very bizarre behavior because we just go
into a room and we run on treadmills and
we do it because obviously we've evolved
to require exercise and uh modernity has
removed exercise as a prerequisite to
most of the things that we need in life.
Um but now there's this gaping hole and
so what we do is we just go to the gym
and we run in place uh to satiate this
physical need. And so you could imagine,
and one might interpret this as
dystopian or utopian, but you could
imagine a world where we've offloaded so
much cognition, but because humans need
to think about things, um, or as a
society, we value it the same way we
value physical fitness that there's now
social pressures to go to these
intellectual gyms. um just to make sure
even though you know you don't need to
do it for work or it's not necessary for
the world to to function but we feel
like there's just value in a human who
knows how to reason about things so we
just you know we go to intellectual gyms
for that and so we might I don't know if
that's utopian or dystopian future but
however we feel about it I would venture
to guess people 500 years ago who looked
at a treadmill would probably feel
similarly
>> 100% well MLST is my intellectual gym by
the way but um [laughter] you know you
spoke about um DNA. Um so um Dawkins of
course wrote this book the the selfish
gene and you said actually that the
value of DNA was not what it creates. So
you know it creates hearts and lungs and
so on but what it enables which is this
evolution process but then it gets to
this concept of what we mean by a meme
in general. So you said that it's it's
an idea or behavior which spreads
contagiously. Um I mean what how do you
think about memes? Um, well, I think
Dawkins did a a wonderful job uh
articulating this idea in a way that's
really understandable. Um, where a meme
is a is a is a concept or a behavior.
So, a meme can be just like the idea um
that individuals should have rights. Um,
or the idea of equality or something
sillier as the idea that we that we
shake hands before uh we sit down for uh
a meeting. And these things because
humans uh can share simulations through
language and we engage in imitation
learning. These ideas or behaviors
propagate throughout societies. Um and
because these things are propagating um
a different form not evolution in the
sense of uh you know genetic evolution
but a form of evolution emerges because
I some ideas will propagate better than
other ideas. So uh by by nature of that
process unfolding uh memes um these
concepts or behaviors actually go
through an evolutionary process. Um so
ideas that that either are viral because
people want to share them with each
other. Um or ideas that somehow support
the survival of the individuals that
hold them. Um those are going to be
ideas that propagate correctly. ideas
that uh negatively affect the survival
of the individuals that hold them or for
whatever reason people do not desire to
share or ideas that are going to do a
worse job um um propagating. And so it's
a really almost brilliant lens to look
at uh human culture um when you reframe
sort of cultural ideas and concepts as
memes uh a different take on a gene uh
that goes through its own sort of
process of iteration which is not my
idea. This is Richard Dawkins's uh
>> Oh yeah. Well, we can we can thank
Richard very much for this. But no, I'm
I'm fascinated with with memes and I
kind of think of language as as being a
collection of memes. But now we're in
this very very interesting space, right?
So um you know before before language we
learned by you know observing physical
skills as performed by other people and
and we could kind of imitate them and so
on. Now we are sharing um you know kind
of simulations basically without
actually needing to see the thing and
that means that we are kind of one step
removed from reality. So all sorts of
memes have cropped up and some of them
are better described as you say in your
book as shared delusions and but they
have some utility as well you know so
they they have this um you know when we
have a common myth for example it might
be a religion it might be a nation state
it allows us to kind of um cooperate
with each other in in a way that we we
wouldn't be able to do before and you
actually cited um some some ideas by
John Surin and and Uvel Harrari in his
book Sapiens on that [snorts]
>> yeah they both have great they
uh you've you've all famously like
popularized this idea. Um but Surl was
one of the original ideiators of it. Um
but what's so powerful about these sort
of shared fictions is they can propagate
much more easily than a human can talk
to everyone in a group. And so because
they propagate much more easily and what
with very high fidelity, it enables me
to meet someone who is a New Yorker who
I never have met before and immediately
have shared views. We we probably both
believe in individual rights. We
probably both believe in uh you know
that money can be used for transacting
things. So I if I give them a dollar,
they'll believe that the dollar will be
used elsewhere or they can give me a
dollar. Um, and you and of course today
it's hard to reason about these things
because there's so many rules in place
that you don't realize it's all a a
shared fiction. So, you know, the reason
we think we believe in money is because
we're like, well, I know that all the
other stores I go to will take this
money. So, that's the reason it works.
But why do they all take the money? It's
this all this this just shared belief
that we all trust that this thing will
will be used um for transacting. And so
because of that it enables really large
groups of people to coordinate um and
and and that is a very powerful aspect
of language. Um but the sort of the
argument I make in in the book which is
is uh is that similar to how genes are
powerful not because of the structures
it creates but because it enables a
process of evolution by which good
structures will emerge. Language is
similar in that sense. It's not what's
powerful about language uh per se is not
that we can engage in these shared
simulations for coordination. It's that
language enables the propagation of
ideas and concepts across generations
which will there thereby go under its
own evolutionary process. So of course
these good ideas that enable survival
are going to emerge. Um and that's
really what's so powerful about about
language. I guess like the arbitrariness
is is quite interesting. So some of them
on the surface don't seem like good
ideas. they just seem like really bad
ideas. And there's this kind of um I
mean I guess you can think about it in
terms of creativity as well, which is
like, you know, for a meme to be
established in in the sphere of possible
memes. Um does it need to have intrinsic
value? And possibly not. You know,
because we're getting into creativity,
is it novelty? Um does it have intrinsic
value? Is it just social proof? You
know, is is the meme does it only exist
because lots of people have been fooled
into thinking it has value. So it's kind
of like exttrinsic value via via social
proof. And then there's like almost a
double on tandra with the meme or a
deeper meme meaning because you talk
about altruism. So the meme itself might
actually be quite a stupid meme but if
it causes altruism so there's actually a
group selection advantage to it then
it's almost like that's the lens of
analysis to understand how good the meme
is.
>> Yeah. the so there's so much cons like
um it's a really fun area of literature
to read through because there's still
like zero consensus as to how language
evolved um and the re one reason why
it's so controversial is the way in
which we disambiguate um and I'll get to
your your question um the the way we
dismbiguate evolutionary arguments is
typically by observing uh gradation in
extant or currently present animals and
so that enables us to observe these
intermediate mediary steps between you
know morphological or uh sort of aspect
of of the body A and morphological
aspect of a body B. And the problem with
language is we have non-human primates
that for the most part don't have any
language and then we have humans that
have very complex language. And all of
the intermediary humans that existed
between uh our divergence with
chimpanzees about 6 million years ago
and our divergence with all all other
modern humans between 50,000 100,000
years ago. Um we don't have they're all
dead. All those lineages are lost. And
so that means that there's this broad
spectrum of of arguments that could be
made between uh you know Chomsky argues
I find this a very strong claim and thus
hard to to defend but there are people
that argue that it happened all at once
or like very rapidly there was like no
language then all of a sudden there's
language and then there's
>> right and there's other arguments that
it was this sort of gradual gradual
process
>> but the one of the most controversial
aspects of language evolution goes to
what you're talking about which is uh
evolutionary arguments for why language
evolved has almost a harder burden of
proof than other adaptations.
So when we argue um uh about the
evolutionary benefit of something like
theory of mind um there's no complex
evolutionary machinations one needs to
conceive of to defend it because you can
see why it would be beneficial for an
individual um uh chimpanzeee to be born
with the ability to infer what's going
on other people's heads because they can
better defend themselves when someone is
going to be mean. They can better figure
out who to trust. They can better climb
the social hierarchy, etc.
But language unless you make take the
chsky view that its primary adaptation
is for thinking. Um but if you hold the
argument that uh language evolved for
communication that's more challenging
because it's it's not valuable for an
individual human to be born with a
little bit of language skill unless
other humans are also engaging in
language as well. And so this then means
that the only benefit is if we're both
sharing true useful information with
each other. And although it seems
intuitive that like well the way this
would function is that a group of humans
that uh are sharing knowledge with each
other is going to survive better than
another group of human that's not and
that's how evolution will ensue. This is
actually quite controversial in
evolutionary biology because that's
invoking something called group
selection which now some people the the
the modern incarnation of this something
called multi-level selection where uh
there's some consensus that yes there
are group level effects um where that
kind of can impact things. Um but
but it's um um but most people think
that group level effects are not nearly
as strong as we would intuit it. And the
issue the issue is the following. If you
have a group of a hundred humans that
use language with each other and then
you have one human that's born that
actually is just going to try and trick
all the others. So all they're going to
do is use language just to to be
disingenuous. It's not at all clear that
that human would be at a disadvantage.
Um and so if people then start in fact
they might be at an advantage relative
to everyone else. And so if you play
that forward over time, language will be
lost because the someone born that's not
going to be tricked by the individual
that's trying to lie to them with
language is actually going to survive
better than the people that have
language skills. And so and so there's
been so much debate throughout um
linguistic evolutionary linguistics
about um these arguments as to how
language evolved. Um I like uh the sort
of there's a great book called the
evolution of language by Fitch. Um and I
think he makes a really great argument.
um around how you know you could think
about this occurring. Um but but a lot
of people argue that it probably started
with something called reciprocal
altruism. And so um the way altruism
exists in the animal kingdom, there's
two forms of accepted uh altruism. One
is something called kin selection which
is quite straightforward. Um I'm going
to I'm willing to sacrifice something.
Other words, share something with an
individual if I share genes with them.
So you know that's easy. reciprocal
altruism we do see in the animal kingdom
which is I'll scratch your back if you
scratch my back but if you start not
scratching my back then I'm gonna stop
scratching your back and so um what this
suggests is in order for language to be
stable in other words it be beneficial
for me to truthfully share information
there needs to be costs to me lying um
and so this is one argument uh that
people people speculate this is one
reason why humans
um uh have such strong sort of uh moral
preferences towards punishing of liars
and outgroups and in-groups because what
we do is uh uh we really try to identify
individuals that are lying. Robin Dunar
has a beautiful argument that this is
why gossip evolved. One way that
evolution can stabilize uh uh the using
language is by virtue of us having a
preference to share moral violations. Um
and so gossip being a tool that uh of
language where if you see someone uh lie
or cheat um and you uh share it with a
bunch of other individuals that becomes
a huge cost to someone lying and
cheating because if one person catches
them then the whole group is aware of
it. And so there's this sort of special
feedback loop that happens where
language skills require uh more uh uh
more punishment of violation to be a
stable strategy. And then the one way
you get that is by uh having more gossip
and making sure there's higher costs to
uh to defecting. So so this is not by
any means like the only story of
language evolution. Um but it's one that
that there's uh you know a lot of
interesting evidence behind. Um there
are some people that argue that the the
feedback loop one emerging idea which I
don't talk about in the book which is I
do think is interesting um is that the
the feedback loop of language evolution
um is actually one in which we try to
detect lying in others. Um so so so and
and they make the counterargument to me
saying that the effect of uh lying is
loss of language. Um there is an
argument that you get the reverse where
um you get really good theory of mind in
humans because we're so sensitive to
trying to detect people who are actually
giving us false information. So still a
lot of controversy around it but um but
the main takeaway is that the the whole
the blanket group level selection
argument that language is obviously
beneficial because once a group has
language they're all going to to survive
better. Um is not a sufficient argument
for language evolution. You need a more
nuanced evolutionary argument as to why
it's a stable strategy for an individual
to be born with superior language skills
or you have to argue that language did
not evolve primarily for communication.
>> You know, now it's quite interesting
first of all that you were writing this
book actually a couple of years ago. So
this was before GPT4 although you did
put a note in about GPT4 and uh you were
speaking about Blake Lemon and he was
this Google engineer and he famously
came out and you know he was convinced
that these things had developed
sentience. Uh I I think much of this
actually hinges on this concept of a
world model. So one view of language
models is that you know they're just
modeling a statistical distribution of
of tokens and that seems quite low
resolution. Like another take is that
they're learning a world model. And what
that means is that rather than just kind
of capturing the the state of language,
they are actually they're they're
simulators. They're generating the
underlying processes of language.
They're capturing the dynamics of
language. How do you say that something
is or is not sentience? especially given
that the models could potentially be so
high resolution that they are generating
the same thing for all intents and
purposes.
>> Yeah, this is where um I don't see
myself as a philosopher, but this is
where I do think scientists need to
include philosophers because when
questions become non-scientific, I think
the scientific instinct is to argue that
we don't draw distinctions between
things that scientists that the
scientific method can't draw a
distinction between. But the problem is
there might be moral differences between
them. So for example, it might be
scientifically impossible for us to have
we have no methodology for
differentiating whether two systems that
look indistinguishable in their outputs
and inputs which one is sentient. And so
scientifically we might say well for for
the because we can't differentiate the
two we're going to say they're the same.
But that doesn't mean they're the same.
That just means that because we have no
methodology for for drawing a
distinction between them.
from a scientific perspective, we're not
going to draw a distinction because
we're entering philosophical territory.
But if you if you take that and then you
start talking about policy implications
and and the actual values we attribute
to them and how we introduce these
things to society, I think we need to
include a sort of philosophy lens here.
Um because it might not actually be the
case that they're the same just because
we can't distinguish them. So that's
just one thought.
>> Other thought um on world models. So, so
one distinction I want to draw because
I've seen a lot of um confusion on the
internet about about the world model
dilemma. Um so there's a difference
between a world model and a model. It is
undeniable that language models have a
model. Um, and all that means is clearly
in order for GBT4 to correctly predict
the next token in these really
complicated language questions, it
clearly has some model of something. Um,
and because we can ask common sense
questions about the world to it and it
answers many of them correct. You can
say this is a model of aspects of our
world without question. I think that
would very hard to argue that's not the
case if you look at the performance of
of GBT4 in many of these these
questions. But what most people mean
when they say a world model is they mean
a specific process of stimulating an
ordered simulating an ordered states of
consequences of different actions
>> and and identifying the the end result
of these actions in your head. Another
way to think about what we mean by role
model is the ability to reason about
interventions and causality. And so so
uh this is the Judea Pearl sort of
argument here which is um with our world
model we can hypothesis test. I can say
I imagine that if I do this thing in the
world I think this will be the
consequence of it because that's what I
see in my head. Now I have a hypothesis.
Now I'm going to actually do that thing
in the world and see if my hypothesis is
correct.
And so that's very different than what's
happening in a language model where its
understanding of the world derives
solely from its input data versus in a
world model my understanding of the
world comes from the delta the
difference between what I hypothesize is
going to happen in the world and then my
actual experience of it. And this
distinction really matters the more we
are going to start offloading our
cognition to these systems because for
example everything that chat GBT knows
is on the basis of its input data. And
so that means if false information or
wrong information is in the input data
chat GBT is going to know that
information. There's there's absolutely
no hypothesis testing embedded into chat
GBT versus our true AGI agent that one
will will be invented. um what it would
do is it's going to hypothesize aspects
of the world and it's going to test its
own hypothesis. And so if you give it
false information, if it reads articles
about how the earth is flat, it's not
going to just start talking about how
the earth is flat. It's going to say,
"Okay, well that is in congruent with my
model of the world, I'm going to now
render some tests where I could
differentiate them and I'm going to
perform those tests and then I'm going
to conclude that the world is not is not
flat." So, so um when one says that
Chachu does not have a world model, I
think some people misinterpret that as
suggesting that it's just dumbly looking
at the statistics um and I think that's
not at all what we're saying in order to
correctly look at the statistics of
language. Clearly, it's built up a very
rich and complex model um of the text
that it's seeing and that's how it's
able to predict the next word so well.
But it's not what most people mean when
we say world model.
>> Yeah. I mean, a couple of things on
that. Yeah. Um I think I think people
conflate the machinations of of language
models with how we represent them
statistically or or abstractly because
if you look at a lot of papers they
actually represent it like a probability
you know like a joint probability
distribution and of course you know the
way that language models work is
completely different to that but you
bringing in some very interesting
things. So first of all we are agents in
the world. So the the agential lens is
quite interesting. We interact with the
world. So we're not just learning from
observational data. It's quite
interesting actually. I was talking with
Nick Chaita, you know, we said, "Oh, why
is it that in our everyday experience,
we see we experience the world in in 4D
color, and he said it's because it's
interactive. So in your experience
plane, you can actually seek new
information, right? You can cade your
eyes, you can get new information in,
you can you can touch things and when
you're doing future or past simulations,
you don't have that interactivity. So
there's something about interactivity
which is really important. But even then
right you know we could you know how far
how far could you go? So a complete
onetoone simulacrim of the world
wouldn't be a particularly good model
and in in physics there is no causality
right. So it's just dynamics. So
causality is actually something which
emerges very very far up. So we're
talking about a model which is an
approximation of the real world which
may or may not include causality. it
probably would because it's an
interactive model and it has this kind
of agential map. But I guess we're just
kind of drawing the line somewhere and
we're saying well that is a world model
and yeah
well I think the um it's I'm actually uh
I'm not sure if even if we rendered
let's think about it if we rendered a
perfect three-dimensional
map of every particle in the universe
>> and and that was the input data to some
infinitely large model. I still would
argue that it is learning something
different than a model that is given
some form of agency where it can
hypothesize rules and then test its own
rules. Now given infinite time it is
possible that those will converge
because given infinite time every
possible hypothesis I could conceive of
will end up showing up in the training
data. So eventually I'll see the
training data of every possible
experiment I could run. Um, if yeah, if
time is infinite, I guess you could
suppose that happens. But what's so
different is there's this dramatic
dimensionality reduction that happens
when you show me something uncertain and
then I can conceive of specifically the
tests I want to run to map the the
uncertain thing to my mental model of
the world. And so that's a very
different way of learning about things.
It's not just input data and then and
then self-supervising on predicting
one's own input data. It's building a
model that can I can simulate possible
outcomes and then hypothesis tests those
outcomes. And so I think you know when
we look at even this is not uniquely
human at all. If you look at uh you know
the way a rat would deal with something
novel in its environment it's drawn to
the novel thing and it explores the
novel thing until it feels like it
understands it.
>> Um and then it will move away. Um, and
so when you show a child an object that
is perplexing, they will touch it, turn
it around, try and understand it until
they feel like they built a model of it.
That simple act is doing something very
different than the self-s supervision we
see in most AI models today because I
see something I'm uncertain about and
I'm valitionally going to create new
training data for me. I'm I know the
training data I want now. I want to see
what happens when I pick it up and I
turn it to the left and I turn it to the
top. A convolutional neural network
doesn't do that. So the way we teach
CNN's to uh understand rotations in 3D
objects is we manipulate the training
data ourselves. Uh we we we a we take
data we take imagery and then we rotate
it a bunch of different ways so that we
are the ones sort of curating the data
set to teach it these things.
>> Yeah.
>> Um but that's different than the way we
learn about things. So I think this is a
key aspect um that's missing from AI
systems today that we're that folks are
working on. Um but that's something
we're going to have to add in.
>> Yeah, completely agree. And it feels
like um I mean you're you're saying
basically what I think which is that
there is um you use the word valition, I
use the word agency. There's a
creativity and an agency gap. And a lot
of that is because we we are agents as
you say we we create our own training
data and we do this active inferencing
and sense making and we build we build
these models in real time and as a
collective intelligence it creates a
kind of divergent search process for
knowledge. It's this epistemic foraging
that we spoke about. GPT is a monolithic
model and you know it does have models
but the models are only learned at train
time. The inference actually happens at
train time and then when you put a
prompt in into GPT you're just
retrieving one of the models that are
already learned a long time ago. It's
not creating a new model in the moment.
So it creates this kind of sclerotic
system rather than this divergent
creative system you know which is what
we experience in biomimetic um
intelligence.
I the the um one sort of mental model I
have of this because there's so so much
debate around so I'd be curious I
haven't put this to the test of uh the
gauntlet of um what other people think
about so maybe in the comments people
will either agree or disagree with this
but I think an interesting uh
alternative experiment or or eval uh of
an AI model which I haven't heard before
is if you give it knowingly false
information in the training data not at
inference time in the training data will
it reject it wholesale and to me this is
this is the distinction which is a agent
that can hypothesis test and intervene
in the world will reject false
information uh you can if you tell it if
you say the world is flat it will know
that the world is not flat um and so uh
versus GBT any data you give it is given
equal weight to every other data so the
only reason it would reject that is if
there's other data in the training set
that it would that it's going to ignore.
Um, and so almost it's almost cheating
because by definition, uh, we know a
language model is going to fail at this
task. The only way you can fix it is if
you give it other data in the training
set. There's no notion of hypothesis
testing versus an agent. Um, the only
way you could get it to be wrong is if
you manipulate its sensors on the actual
hypothesis testing of that it does. You
can of course manipulate it by you know
when it does these tests you change the
actual test which happens in the book
threebody problem which is an amazing
book where aliens manipulate our
experiments. Um but anyway I think that
that's another way to eval these these
systems which is uh does it can it
figure out uh that you're giving it
false information and reject it.
>> Yeah 100%. Um a couple of things though.
So there's something magic about the h
having aential density in in the system
right. So when you have something like
GPT um just to make it statistically
tractable it's generally doing a kind of
low entropy search and what you know
what what I mean by that is it's just
looking for the baseline patterns it's
not doing a lot of exploration it's not
searching outside of the um the main
sources of statistical regularity
whereas when you have a divergence um
you know in the search process so you
have all of these individual agents
doing their own things um as a system
it's much more of a high entropy search
which means you're actually bringing in
lots of new information to solve
problems in creative and interesting
ways. is. But in the physical world
though, um it's quite interesting,
right? Because the problems come from
the physical world. So the trees get big
now. The giraffes need to have a a long
neck in order to eat the leaves from the
trees. And this whole thing just rinses
and repeats. So you know that the
environment produces novel solutions and
then like we see this divergence and we
find novel um uh you know creative
solutions to to the problems that get
generated. But in the mtic sphere it's
so much more difficult than that, right?
because the the problems and the guard
rails aren't constrained in in the way
that they are in the physical world. So,
for example, we have capitalism or we
have the nation states and again there's
all kinds of interesting divergence
going in different directions, but like
it doesn't seem like there are the same
pressures that ground the thing to
reality.
>> Well, yeah, I think it's definitely not
uh grounded in truth. Um, it's tethering
to truth is it's tethering towards uh
knowingly false information that leads
me to take actions that will hurt my
survival will fade. But false
information that helps me survive better
will propagate freely um or is at least
neutral. Um and you know another way
this shows up is in uh this is where I
I'll go into uh maybe some pontificating
uh
>> please. But but where uh where I think
there is sort of mimemetic evolution
that can drive us away even from things
like happiness. So, so if we think about
what are systems of coordination that
survive, they're systems of domination
uh of um of militarism. Um if you take
two groups, one had let's say two you
take two groups of individuals, let's
say one is really happy and calm and
they see no desire for domination and
they do not attempt to innovate and
build more technology. Another they're
unhappy but they're super aggressive and
they want power and they want to expand.
these ideas will die out. Um uh and so
so what what this suggests what's
important and I think I talked about
this in one of our previous
conversations is delineating in my view
uh the Darwinian component of what does
survive from the moral component of what
is right or wrong. Um because it is
definitely not the case uh that what is
right what survives is definitionally
right. Um, it is absolutely possible
that the things that survive and do well
evolutionarily are not the things that
we feel like are aligned morally. Um,
and that of course is not to propose a a
a correct or incorrect system, but it is
an important distinction to draw when
we're trying to decide what do we deem
to be morally right or wrong. Um, so I
think that's just one example of what
you're saying where um the ideas that
propagate successfully might not be the
ones that are truth. They might also not
be the ones that we deem to be moral or
or not even be the ones that lead to
human happiness. They're just ones that
do a good job keeping humans alive and
reproducing of the idea.
>> Yeah. So on on that then I mean people
say that language models you know they
confabulate and um they they don't
preserve epistemic factfulness. But you
could also argue the same thing about
us, right? So we actually confabulate
everything. We don't really have goals.
We just kind of um generate these post
hoc confabulations and then we explain
our behavior and we kind of pretend that
that was what we wanted to do that we
had beliefs and so on. that we just kind
of make it up as as we go along using
this kind of active inference. Um, so I
guess that the question is like we do
think of ourselves as being like even
though we are emotional and subjective
and like you know like we believe in
religion and lots of things that that we
presumably made up but but we have
Wikipedia. We have objectivity even
though it's an illusion, right? There's
there's no such thing even like general
relativity. It's not as objective as as
we think. Like if you keep asking why
and why and why, it just kind of
disintegrates into incoherence. But
there seems to be some objective
structure which is preserved. And how is
that explained given that our brain
simulations are um you know they don't
seem to select for for truthfulness. I
think the desire to say is are humans
better or worse than chat GBT is almost
like a a red herring where I look at
chat GBT as like an alien. It's like an
alien brain. And there are certain
things it does that are clearly better
than us. I mean information retrieval in
chat GBT blows a human without a
question. So like in many ways it's way
better than humans.
>> Um and but but there are certain things
that human brains do uh that chache does
not have. Um and if we're trying to
build humanlike intelligence, there's
certain inspiration we can garner from
from human brains. Um so I think uh you
know there's a component of our model
based sort of uh you know rendering a
plan and then executing that plan that
has a level of explanability that is
unique relative to a system that uh is
sort of um just iteratively predicting
the next token. But we also do the same
thing that chat GBT does. When we make
model free choices and then you say why
did you do that thing? What we engage in
is exactly as you're describing a post
hawk explanation. Um because I didn't
render a plan. I was just walking down
the street. Um and you say why did you
move your your foot there as opposed to
two inches to the right. What I'm going
to do is render a post hawk explanation
of why I did that. But I didn't really
think about it. I'm just explaining it
after the fact. Um so so it's definitely
the case that humans have that
component. Um but it means there's also
another component which we which I would
argue is is unique and important which
is our ability um to pause render a plan
and then execute against that plan. But
the key thing that's that I I think is
the dividing line between these models
and us is the ability to render
hypotheses and make interventions in the
world. That's the like that's the key
thing. And so it it's not the case that
our brain has the true uh um uh
objective state of the world in our
head. I don't think that's uh there
might be components of objective truth
in ChachiBT that it contains that we
don't have and I think in its
information retrieval it has probably in
some ways more aspects of reality than I
do uh in terms of it having read all of
Wikipedia and answering questions about
biology that I don't even know. Um but
there are also components of the world
that the human brain has rendered and
contains that chatbt does not because of
our ability to make hypotheses and
intervene and learn the causal structure
of the world. And I think that is the
the dividing line. But it's I wouldn't I
wouldn't say it's because the human
brain knows the objective state of the
world and Chad GBT does not.
>> Max Bennett, it's been an absolute honor
to have you on MLST. Everyone at home,
you need to buy his book immediately. It
is a a wonderful, wonderful book, Max.
You did such an amazing job of bringing
all these things together. And we've now
spoken for 4 and a half hours going
through the last three chapters. And my
god, it's been an honor. Thank you so
much. Oh, it's been my pleasure. Thank
you for having me.
>> Beautiful. Okay.